<transcript>
<page num="1">

<folioref id="0006">
fol.128v
</folioref>
 
<addressleaf id="6236">
<section id="5521" Section="endorsement" Place="none">
March 31 to My L. Thresuro
<super id="0009" replace="">
r
</super>
 
<underline id="0012">
1589
</underline>
.
</section>
</addressleaf>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0019">
fol.127r
</folioref>
 
<lettertext id="6239">
<section id="5524" Section="lateraddition" Place="top_left">
Belgia 1589 31 March To my lord Treasurer
</section>
<newline/>
It maye please yo
<super id="0026" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. as at the writtinge of my last, the towne
<newline/>
of 
<place id="5527" place_id="Geertruidenberg">
Geertrudenberche
</place>
 contineweth besieged: The first attempt
<newline/>
that they without gave against it was at the walter
<newline/>
syde, w
<super id="0032" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 fyer workes, and other artificiall engines, wherew
<super id="0035" replace="ith">
th
</super>
<newline/>
they had filled a shippe, supposinge by it to have cast
<newline/>
downe a great 
<image name="par"/>
te of the walles, and to have sett many howses
<newline/>
a fire. But it proved in tryall a weake devyse, scorned
<newline/>
at by suche as stoode upon the walles, and that litell harme
<newline/>
that it did fell upon them selves. There followed uppon
<newline/>
it along batterie, w
<super id="0045" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 continewed divers dayes, and some nightes,
<newline/>
untill the breache was esteemed resonable: and then sondrie
<newline/>
of the chiefest in place, as the 
<person id="5530" person_id="Solms">
count of Solmes
</person>
, 
<person id="5533" person_id="Nassau, Phillip">
count phillipp
</person>
,
<newline/>
<person id="5536" person_id="Villiers">
Mareshall Villers
</person>
, and others gave the assault w
<super id="0051" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 a greate
<newline/>
furie, comminge to it w
<super id="0055" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 Flat bottom boates. But they were
<newline/>
forced to retire immediatly, findinge the resistance of the
<newline/>
garrison very resolut and desperat, and the meanes to assault
<newline/>
out of their boates, full of comber and disadvantage. The
<newline/>
Mareshall Villers was shotte into the knee, but like to recover
<newline/>
it quickely. The Towe viceadmiralls of 
<place id="5539" place_id="Holland">
Holand
</place>
 &amp; 
<place id="5542" place_id="Zeeland">
Zelande
</place>
<newline/>
were shott into the armes: w
<super id="0064" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
  it is thought the will be forced
<newline/>
To cutt of. A Brother of 
<person id="5545" person_id="Brederode">
Mons
<super id="0068" replace="ieur">
r
</super>
  Brederode
</person>
 was slaine,
<newline/>
and divers captaynes besydes, of good account and 
<scharfes_s id="0072" replace="ser">
s
</scharfes_s>
vice, partly
<newline/>
slaine, and 
<image name="par"/>
tly hurt: as also a great 
<image name="par"/>
te of 
<person id="5548" person_id="Maurice">
count Maurice
</person>
<newline/>
gard, and of the common Souldiers. uppon the newes of 
<newline/>
This repulse, This 
<person id="5551" person_id="Council of State">
counsell of State
</person>
 made request by
<newline/>
Their letters Sent to the camp, To the 
<person id="5554" person_id="States General">
States
</person>
 deputies
<newline/>
There, That they wold use my presence and assistaunce
<newline/>
for effectinge Some accord: whereto they never made
<newline/>
answere, nor since the siege beganne 
<deletion id="0085">
nether
</deletion>
 
<insertion id="0088">
never
</insertion>
 writt hither
<newline/>
To any of those assemblyes for any advyse. neverthelesse
<newline/>
for a further discharge of my dutye in this place, and for
<newline/>
That it was a common speeche of the people, that 
<person id="5557" person_id="Wingfield, J">
S
<super id="0094" replace="ir">
r
</super>
<newline/>
John Winckefeld
</person>
 had intelligence w
<super id="0098" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 the ennemye, I writt
<newline/>
a letter to S
<super id="0102" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 John whereby I requested him to be
<newline/>
advertised from him, if any likelehoode were left among those
<newline/>
in the towne, That I might be an instrument of a good
<newline/>
composityon. I required him farther in hir 
<person id="5560" person_id="Elizabeth">
Ma
<super id="0108" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
</person>
 name, to
<newline/>
Take a speciall care, That the towne might not faule
<newline/>
into the ennemyes possession. This letter I sent open to
<newline/>
The camp, desiringe it might be sent, or Suppressed, as
<newline/>
The count and the rest should most behoofull. howbeit
<newline/>
They sent it immediately, and w
<super id="0116" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 muche adoe it was
<newline/>
receaved, and the answere given not by S
<super id="0120" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 John, but by
<newline/>
The rest, That they wold have no further dealinge
<newline/>
w
<super id="0125" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 hir Ma
<super id="0128" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
: or any of hir ministers, for that my L.
<newline/>
willoughbyes proceeding
<image name="es"/>
 were discovered sufficiently.
<newline/>
The cause of w
<super id="0134" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 answere proceded hereof. The count not
<newline/>
willinge To come againe unto the assault, Thought by other
<newline/>
practises To make a devisyon among those of the garrison,
<newline/>
and there upon Sent a certaine act unto them, w
<super id="0141" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 my 
<person id="5563" person_id="Bertie, P">
L.
<newline/>
willoughby
</person>
 long sence, gave unto the count, To [asseure] him
<newline/>
<folioref id="0147">
fol.127v
</folioref>
 of his good meaninge for the delivery of the towne into his hands
<newline/>
The sight of that act made a Sudden allteration among them
<newline/>
for whereas before they pretended still To houlde for hir Ma
<super id="0152" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
They began then To disclaime, and to use railinge speeches
<newline/>
against my lord. and the inglishe natyon, that went about
<newline/>
in that order To betraye them. and howe they intreated S
<super id="0158" replace="ir">
r
</super>
<newline/>
John uppon it I knowe not yet certainelye: but it is 
<newline/>
bruted abroade, that they have him In custodye. my letter
<newline/>
comming thither, upon the delivery of this act, tooke no other
<newline/>
effect: and Since continewallye, they have answered the
<newline/>
ennemyes fires, and sent unto them three out of their garrison
<newline/>
To capitulat about yelding up the towne: w
<super id="0168" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 whome it is
<newline/>
also Sayd, That the ducke him self being come to 
<place id="5568" place_id="Breda">
Breda
</place>
<newline/>
hath had conference and hath allready skirmyshed w
<super id="0173" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 the
<newline/>
count. heereuppon both he and the rest there 
<deletion id="0177">
wery
</deletion>
 very
<newline/>
much perplexed, Sent yesterdaye To the counsell
<newline/>
hither, requesting that I wold come in 
<image name="par"/>
son, and make
<newline/>
Triall if better Succese wold come of it. I made an-
<newline/>
swere, That if that course had bin taken at first, when
<newline/>
hir Ma
<super id="0187" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 name was used and respected in the towne, I
<newline/>
douted not, but they might have bin brought To some tollerable
<newline/>
condicions. But nowe the ennemye beinge come to the walles
<newline/>
it seemed a desperat case: never the lesse I referred my
<newline/>
<scharfes_s id="0194" replace="ser">
s
</scharfes_s>
vice To the counsell
<image name="es"/>
 disposition. requestinge Them to
<newline/>
conferre many mens advertysement
<image name="es"/>
 together, towchinge
<newline/>
the states of the towne, and then To resolve, as they
<newline/>
should thinke best, about my imployement: wherein they
<newline/>
bestowed somme tyme presently, and found it all to late,
<newline/>
expecting letters every hower of the ennemyes entrye and
<newline/>
The retraicte of our men: Not to troble yo
<super id="0205" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 Lordship
<newline/>
w
<super id="0209" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 the relac
<overline id="0212" replace="io">
o
</overline>
n of all 
<image name="par"/>
ticular accident
<image name="es"/>
, upon the
<newline/>
occasyon of this enterprice, and the unhappy successe,
<newline/>
There is nothinge heere but feare, &amp; troble, and confu-
<newline/>
sion, as well amonge the better Sort as the co
<overline id="0220" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
on people,
<newline/>
Some fewe crienge out against S
<super id="0225" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 John Winckefeld, and
<newline/>
The Inglishe natyon, but the farre greater 
<image name="par"/>
t against
<newline/>
The authors of the action: w
<super id="0231" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I can not yet learne
<newline/>
To have bin any other Then the count, 
<person id="5571" person_id="Oldenbarnvelt">
Barnevelt,
</person>
 &amp;
<newline/>
Villiers; but Barnevelt in speciall, whose greedy
<newline/>
desire of revenge against those of the towne, and my L.
<newline/>
willughby hath wrought this effect. moreover their delivery
<newline/>
of my L. Willoughbyes act is generally condemned as a 
<newline/>
dishonorable dealinge Toward
<image name="es"/>
 my lord, and very incon-
<newline/>
siderate, in respect of them selves, for by it they exclu-
<newline/>
ded themselves from all kinde of hoope of any good com-
<newline/>
position. all their allegations in excuse of this exploict
<newline/>
are very frivolous &amp; fained. They saye That those of
<newline/>
The towne have bin practisinge a longe tyme w
<super id="0246" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 the
<newline/>
ennemye, That the losse of the towne, is of no suche
<newline/>
importance, as men commonly give out, That the incove-
<newline/>
nyence, w
<super id="0252" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 wold have ensewed in other garrisons, if 
<newline/>
<folioref id="0256">
fol.128r
</folioref>
 The insolencie of those of Geertrudenberche should have bin
<newline/>
wincked at, must needes have done Them great harme:
<newline/>
w
<super id="0261" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 other like shiftes: and devises, both untrue, and of no
<newline/>
moment. In effect the state of these provinc
<image name="es"/>
 is weake
<newline/>
at this present,Then it hathe bin these many yeares, &amp;
<newline/>
unlesse by hir Ma
<super id="0268" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
  extraordinarye assistaunce, and counsell
<newline/>
it be presently holpen, there is litell apparance, that
<newline/>
They can hould it long. The losse of this Towne of
<newline/>
Geertrudenberge, the absence of hir Ma
<super id="0277" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 lieutenant
<newline/>
The w
<super id="0281" replace="ith">
th
</super>
drawinge of forces, and the imperfectyon of this
<newline/>
government, are great opportunities To drawe the ennemy
<newline/>
onward, and To dismaye The people. In w
<super id="0286" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 respect
<newline/>
I doe expect nothinge more, then to knowe hir Ma
<super id="0290" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
<newline/>
intention: the want whereof I must needes confesse to
<newline/>
yo
<super id="0295" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. doth Some what discourage me, as it is also
<newline/>
a lett That I can not negotiat So effectually nor
<newline/>
extend my 
<scharfes_s id="0300" replace="ser">
s
</scharfes_s>
vice. to so many good purposes, as other
<newline/>
wyse I might. Whereuppon I beseche yo
<super id="0304" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. againe
<newline/>
as in my last, That Some Speedy order maye
<newline/>
be taken for good correspondence, referringe The rela-
<newline/>
tyon of these occurrenc
<image name="es"/>
 to hir highenes and to my 
<person id="5574" person_id="Privy Council">
LL
</person>
 
<deletion id="0311">
the
</deletion>
<newline/>
of the counsell, to yo
<super id="0315" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 wisdome, and good pleasure:
<newline/>
<section id="5577" Section="subscription" Place="none">
wherew
<super id="0319" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 I Take my humble leave. from the Hage 
<newline/>
Marche 31 89.
</section>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
