<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="1381">
<folioref id="1230">
fol.222r
</folioref>
 It is expressed in her 
<person id="3848" person_id="Elizabeth">
Ma
<super id="1237" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
</person>
 l
<overline id="1240" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
 to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 
<person id="3851" person_id="States General">
States,
</person>
 and also sette
<newline/>
downe in my Instructions, That if they shall not con-
<newline/>
descend to some present satisfaction, her Hig
<super id="1243" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 is resol-
<newline/>
ved to calle away her forces. This may seeme
<newline/>
in my opinion, to implie a purpose in her Ma
<super id="1262" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 to
<newline/>
continue her forces there, if soe be they doe agree
<newline/>
to give her good contentment./ It may
<newline/>
please your H. in this point, to understand of her
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="1259" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 what aunswear I shall make, if they put me
<newline/>
to that question, or whether it be her meaning,
<newline/>
that I should hold them in suspence, pretending
<newline/>
that I knowe not howe her Hig
<super id="1256" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 is affected.
<newline/>
<newline/>
Moreover it may be gathered by the forme of those 
<newline/>
speeches, that the revocation of her subjects, and an
<newline/>
open protestation against their ingratitude, is all 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
course of proceeding resolved against them, in case 
<newline/>
of their refusall: which to signifie my conceat, is
<newline/>
no sufficient terror: for that I thincke there are not
<newline/>
many, that wilbe very much moved with the want 
<newline/>
of her forces, if they might be so excused for 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
payment of their debt. And therfore for my part,
<newline/>
if her Ma
<super id="1293" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 can lyke it, I would signifie thus
<newline/>
muche more, That they will force her in 
<image name="thorn"/>
e ende
<newline/>
to take some other kinde of course, then is either
<newline/>
agreable to her princely disposition, or to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e singular
<newline/>
affection which she hath evermore boren to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e good
<newline/>
of those Contreis. This kinde, or the lyke, of
<newline/>
threatning insinuation, will putt them somewhat
<newline/>
in a muse, what may be more intended, and drawe
<newline/>
them happely the sooner to a good resolution.
<newline/>
<newline/>
Whereas her Hig
<super id="1332" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 doth permitte, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at if by diligent
<newline/>
inspection into their condition, I finde 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Provinces
<newline/>
unable to grant the full demaunde of a hundred
<newline/>
thousand poundes, I shall give a secret hope, so
<newline/>
<image name="thorn"/>
at they will make her a convenient offer, (albeyt
<newline/>
I have no warrant to accept a lesser portion), that
<newline/>
I will second them therein with my l
<overline id="3854" replace="ettres">
res
</overline>
 to her Ma
<super id="1301" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
.
<newline/>
<folioref id="1305">
fol.222v
</folioref>
 Howe farre they wilbe moved with my promes[se in]
<newline/>
that case, whose credit with her Hig
<super id="1326" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 they [knowe]
<newline/>
to be not better, then her late displeasure tow[ardes]
<newline/>
me, and 
<image name="thorn"/>
e l
<overline id="1329" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s which I carie discover app[arantly]
<newline/>
I leave to your H. to consider. Forwhere her [Majestie]
<newline/>
doth not shewe, that she respecteth her Mini[ster, it]
<newline/>
can never be expected, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at others in other Con[treis]
<newline/>
will either imagine it of themselves, or hope [to speede]
<newline/>
of their purpose, by the meanes of his endev[ors.]
<newline/>
It may also please
 you to informe me of her [Majesties]
<newline/>
pleasure, whether I shall presse them precis[sely, to]
<newline/>
come to an audit of the accounts, and not [hearken]
<newline/>
to any offer of other composition, wheron p[erhaps]
<newline/>
they would deliberat, if they thought it w[ould be]
<newline/>
embraced; not for any disadvantage, that [they]
<newline/>
thincke they shall receave, by coming to a [reckning]
<newline/>
but as I have heard say among them, to sh[unne the]
<newline/>
occasions of contention, and further incon[venience,]
<newline/>
For by all probabilitie they will stand very [stiffly]
<newline/>
upon many defalcations, as by some notes [that I]
<newline/>
have made, and exhibited by writing unt[o my]
<newline/>
<person id="3857" person_id="Burghley">
L. T
<overline id="1354" replace="resure">
re
</overline>
r
</person>
, it may appeere very plainely.
<newline/>
<newline/>
Moreover I am assured, that they will ne[ver send]
<newline/>
their Deputies so sufficiently autorised, [as that]
<newline/>
it shalbe left unto them, to compounde [every]
<newline/>
difference that may rise upon the account [but]
<newline/>
still they must be forced, to send home un[to their]
<newline/>
Provinces, which will undoubtedly prove a [very long]
<newline/>
peece of worke, and turne her Ma
<super id="1351" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 in [many]
<newline/>
thinges to more prejudice then profit.
<newline/>
<newline/>
It may also steede me in my service, to kn[owe to]
<newline/>
what su
<overline id="1367" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
e their whole debt doth amount, [by her]
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="1370" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 bookes, to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e ende I may thereafter fr[ame my]
<newline/>
answear to their offers, and other co
<overline id="1364" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
unica[tions.]
<newline/>
<newline/>
And if in any other mater I shall neede yo[ur]
<newline/>
decision, I will request it by worde at my re[paire]
<newline/>
unto your H.
</lettertext>
<newline/>
</page>
</transcript>
