<transcript>
<page num="1">
<addressleaf id="0560">
<folioref id="0541">
fol.104v
</folioref>
 
<section id="0557" Section="endorsement" Place="none">
L. T
<overline id="0554" replace="resure">
re
</overline>
r Fe
<abbreviation id="0551" replace="bruary">
b
</abbreviation>
 22 1594
</section>
<newline/>
<section id="0547" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
D
<super id="0544" replace="">
r
</super>
 Birchs Memoirs Vol. 1 Page 209 [.]
</section>
</addressleaf>
<newline/>
<lettertext id="0536">
<folioref id="0002">
fol.101r
</folioref>
<newline/>
May it please your good L. to that effect 
<image name="thorn"/>
at I writte 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 14 of this moneth,
<newline/>
there have bin certaine deputed in 
<image name="thorn"/>
e meeting of the 
<person id="8600" person_id="States General">
States,
</person>
 to come in con-
<newline/>
ference with me, about my proposition, and this they have delivered from
<newline/>
<image name="thorn"/>
e rest of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Assemblie, That they were greatly perplexed, through those
<newline/>
demandes of restituion, not knowing how to frame 
<image name="thorn"/>
e course of their procee-
<newline/>
ding. For though they can not but acknowledge, and doe it most willing-
<newline/>
ly, that through her 
<person id="8603" person_id="Elizabeth">
Ma
<super id="0018" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
</person>
 succors, next to God, they are in farre better
<newline/>
state of securitie and assurance, then they have bin heeretofore for many
<newline/>
yeares together, yet they have not attayned to that abilitie and power, as
<newline/>
they can therwithall discharge their debte unto her Ma
<super id="8606" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
. They alleage
<newline/>
many lettes, but nothing soe muche, as 
<image name="thorn"/>
e intollerable burthen of their
<newline/>
extraordinarie subsidies, which have growen upon them more and more,
<newline/>
for these fower or five yeares: and are raised of late to a very highe
<newline/>
su
<overline id="0204" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
e, occasioned in part by their offensive exploites, and partly by their 
<newline/>
often and chargeable relieving of the 
<person id="8609" person_id="Navarre">
F
<abbreviation id="0031" replace="rench">
r
</abbreviation>
 King
</person>
 in his manifold distre-
<newline/>
sses. By reason whereof they doe inferre, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at 
<image name="thorn"/>
e chiefe contributing Pro-
<newline/>
vinces are farre in arrierages, and pay excessive summes of mony, for
<newline/>
the use of that they have borowed. And though it might be surmised
<newline/>
that they have aided the Kinge, not soe much in regarde of his urgent
<newline/>
necessitie, as de gayet
<image name="e_acute"/>
 de coeur, and to winne his affection, for hidden
<newline/>
respectes, yet they protest therupon with very greate vehemencie, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at
<newline/>
they were evermore farre from any suche jollitie, and would not have
<newline/>
him to enjoy a foote of grounde in their Contrey. For that which drewe
<newline/>
them on to helpe and assist him, was 
<image name="thorn"/>
e generall consideration of his
<newline/>
condition and their owne: and they made this account, that for as
<newline/>
muche as her Hig
<super id="0089" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 did support him with her forces, if they in lyke 
<newline/>
manner should strayne their Estate to upholde him a little, it would
<newline/>
both be a meanes to save him from falling, and to divert the Enemie
<newline/>
from themselves: whereas otherwise if those of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e league, had pre-
<newline/>
vayled against him, these Provinces at last must have bearen alone
<newline/>
the weight of these warres, and then bin subject in the ende, and her
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="8612" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 no lesse, to an apparant great nomber of most perilous incon-
<newline/>
veniences. And whereas it maye be argued that their late
<newline/>
reduction of 
<deletion id="0060">
soe
</deletion>
 so many good townes, hath both greatly assured the State
<newline/>
of these 
<place id="8618" place_id="United Provinces">
Provinces
</place>
 and richely augmented their general meanes,
<newline/>
wherby they are inabled to some portion of remboursement, they make
<newline/>
remonstrance to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Contrarie, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at in every of those Provinces they have
<newline/>
rather bin surcharged, then any thing eased hitherto: and that
<newline/>
<folioref id="0068">
fol.101v
</folioref>
 by reason of the excessive charges of newe garrisons, of necessarie repara-
<newline/>
tions, fortifications, and other extraordinarie occasions, and because
<newline/>
the boores Contribution is very little bettered of that it was in former
<newline/>
tymes. Moreover, they say they finde it in debating very doubt-
<newline/>
full and dangerous, in w
<super id="0078" replace="hat">
at
</super>
 sorte they should proceede for 
<image name="thorn"/>
e aunswer-
<newline/>
ring of her Hig
<super id="0086" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 to my proposition. For in a mater of that qualitie
<newline/>
to make a resolute aunswear, without 
<image name="thorn"/>
e privitie and good lyking of
<newline/>
<image name="thorn"/>
e Provinces, and people, they dare not of themselves, and it will not
<newline/>
stand for good: and then to acquaint the vulgar sorte with her Ma
<super id="0095" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
<newline/>
demandes, were to make it alsoe knowne to all the Enemies Provinces
<newline/>
and soe to all men in generall: wherupon it would be bruited, That
<newline/>
her Hig
<super id="0110" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 hath withdrawen her accoustomed assistance, and hath re-
<newline/>
quyred present paiment of her monies disbursed: which they are mighti-
<newline/>
ly all afraid would turne very quickly to their infinit detriment
<newline/>
aswell for that 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Enemie, who is now in all apparance at a very great
<newline/>
after deale, will be hartened therby, and put in practise new designes
<newline/>
and multiplie his forces by all possible meanes, as because on the other
<newline/>
syde the people of these Contreis, will be caste downe in courage, and
<newline/>
despaire of withstanding the puissance of the Spaniard. For where
<newline/>
they might have hoped after soe many yeares endevo
<super id="0117" replace="">
rs
</super>
, so large con-
<newline/>
tributions, and soe many late victories, to reape some solace and ease of
<newline/>
their burdens and travels, if nowe they should perceave that for
<newline/>
many yeares heereafter, their taxes and exactions will fall a great de[ale]
<newline/>
more heavy, then they have bin heeretofore, first by meanes of their
<newline/>
ordinarie and extraordinarie charges of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e warres, and then by the losse
<newline/>
of her Ma
<super id="0126" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 forces, and most of all by this remboursement, it were
<newline/>
very greatly to be doubted, that they will runne a wrong course in the
<newline/>
heate of their dislyke. For that it yt which they affirme to be a 
<newline/>
principall cause, of their late intertaining of this English regiment
<newline/>
<image name="thorn"/>
at 
<image name="thorn"/>
e actions of their warres might be countenanced alwayes with the
<newline/>
name, and opinion, and reporte of assistance continued to them by 
<newline/>
her Hig
<super id="8621" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 in soe much as they pretend that for 
<image name="thorn"/>
e most the meaner
<newline/>
multitude are noe otherwise yet informed, but that they serve as a part
<newline/>
of Auxiliarie forces, and are in pay of her Ma
<super id="0141" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 soe as alwayes they
<newline/>
have founde in all the tyme of these troubles, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at they have not onley
<newline/>
made warres, and annoyed 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Enemie, with the aide of men and mony
<newline/>
but with very opinions and conceats, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at they were favored and pro-
<newline/>
ected by 
<image name="thorn"/>
e greatnesse of her Ma
<super id="0150" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
. These thinges
<newline/>
<folioref id="0154">
fol.102r
</folioref>
 thus delivered, they sayed they were alsoe charged to participat unto
<newline/>
me the 
<person id="8624" person_id="James VI">
Scottish Kinges
</person>
 letter, and his request by 
<person id="8627" person_id="Stewart, Colonel">
Coronel Stewart
</person>
,
<newline/>
where of they told me the contents, and then read the letter to me,
<newline/>
and the Coronels Instructions translated into Frenche, which I send
<newline/>
heereinclosed copied truely by the originals. Their speeche unto
<newline/>
me upon it was this in substance, That they for themselves were
<newline/>
nothing well Instructed of the state of the King, nor of those pro-
<newline/>
ceedings of his rebels: but if it were soe as those writings imported,
<newline/>
and they had further understoode by the Coronels relation, there
<newline/>
was great occasion offered, to moove her Ma
<super id="0170" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 and them, and as
<newline/>
many as are embarked in this common cause together, to heede 
<super id="0167" replace="">
it
</super>
 in
<newline/>
good season, and to affourd the Kinge a rounde assistance.
<newline/>
For 
<deletion id="0176">
might
</deletion>
 
<insertion id="0179">
sith
</insertion>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Enemie speede no better in his former attemptes, all
<newline/>
men might conjecture, 
<insertion id="0184">
<image name="thorn"/>
at
</insertion>
 he would not lette slippe a fitte opportunitie,
<newline/>
to make a breach by Scotland, for the assaulting of 
<place id="8630" place_id="England">
England,
</place>
 and
<newline/>
soe to compasse all at ease, both heere and in France, all his other
<newline/>
dessignes. For their owne partes, they for their abilitie, would be
<newline/>
willing to doe any thinge, to meete with those dangers: not sturred
<newline/>
unto it, as some men might imagine, for some secret purpose, but
<newline/>
onely in regarde of the generall cause: which provoked them at first
<newline/>
to assist 
<image name="thorn"/>
e K. of France, and doth move them at this time, to tender
<newline/>
the Estate of the Scottish Kinge, and if her Hig
<super id="0201" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 in lyke manner in
<newline/>
her Irish co
<overline id="0198" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
otions, should have any kinde of neede, to use their
<newline/>
meanes or service there, they would stretch their strength to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e utter-
<newline/>
most to accomplish her desires. And this they uttered with
<newline/>
wordes of great assurance and earnestnesse. They concluded
<newline/>
in fine, that first for the matter of remboursement, they would
<newline/>
laye their allegations open to her Hig
<super id="0213" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 before suche tyme as they
<newline/>
would publish her message to the Provinces, and would beseech
<newline/>
her to ballance 
<image name="thorn"/>
e weight of their reasons with her Princely conside-
<newline/>
reation. They expected within a sevenight the co
<overline id="0224" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
ing of the
<newline/>
Deputies of 
<place id="8633" place_id="Gueldres">
Gueldres
</place>
 and 
<place id="8636" place_id="Overijssel">
Overissel,
</place>
 who were busied in those quar-
<newline/>
ters in persuading the people to this yeares contribution. Assone
<newline/>
as they were returned, I should presently receave their aunswear
<newline/>
in writing: they prayed 
<insertion id="0234">
me
</insertion>
 the whyle to intimat soe much by letter
<newline/>
to her Ma
<super id="0231" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
, lest perhaps it should be deemed, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at they have an
<newline/>
intention to use some delay. And then secondly they
<newline/>
<folioref id="0238">
fol.102v
</folioref>
 requested me in the name of the States, sith they could not well determine
<newline/>
what course to embrace in the foresaid motion of the Kinge of Scottes,
<newline/>
<image name="thorn"/>
at I in that respect would franckely co
<overline id="0250" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
unicat my counsaile unto them
<newline/>
to witte what I thought would best accorde, both with her Ma
<super id="0247" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 accep-
<newline/>
tance, and the pleasuring of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Kinge: because it was their full desire
<newline/>
to proceede in those actions with good correspondence, and not otherwise.
<newline/>
<newline/>
I made my aunswear to this effect, That as touching those pointes,
<newline/>
which they had proposed, to manifest first their want and unabilitie
<newline/>
to satisfie her Ma
<super id="0263" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 and then the danger of dealing with the people
<newline/>
therein, they might very well presume, that her Hig
<super id="0266" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 had examined
<newline/>
those reasons already, and that their Agent in England had pleaded
<newline/>
them often, and that she thought them insufficient, to dissuade her
<newline/>
from her purpose. For where they doe complaine 
<image name="thorn"/>
at 
<image name="thorn"/>
e annual
<newline/>
burden of their extraordinarie contributions, doth lie 
<insertion id="0273">
soe
</insertion>
 heavie upon 
<newline/>
the Contrey, it was easie to demonstrat 
<image name="thorn"/>
at 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Contrey was in case to
<newline/>
perfourme a greater mater. They have now in contribution, which
<newline/>
they had not heeretofore, when they treated with her Ma
<super id="0284" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 the grea-
<newline/>
test part of 
<place id="8639" place_id="Brabant">
Brabant
</place>
 and 
<place id="8642" place_id="Flanders">
Flanders,
</place>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Ommelandes, 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 
<place id="8645" place_id="Drenthe">
Drent,
</place>
 
<place id="8648" place_id="Twente">
Twent,
</place>
<newline/>
<place id="8651" place_id="Lingen">
Linghen,
</place>
 the Landes of 
<place id="8654" place_id="Limburg">
Limbourgh
</place>
 and 
<place id="8657" place_id="Valkenburg">
Wilkembourgh,
</place>
 and sondrie other
<newline/>
quarters, which yeald them every monneth a very riche revenue:
<newline/>
besides 
<image name="thorn"/>
at Guelderland and 
<place id="8660" place_id="Zutphen">
Zutphan,
</place>
 and also Ovverissel doe paye a
<newline/>
farre greater subsidie, then in former tymes. They are also enriched
<newline/>
exceedingly, by reason of their imposts in townes lately taken as in
<newline/>
<place id="8663" place_id="Niemegen">
Nieumeghen,
</place>
 Zutphan, 
<place id="8666" place_id="Deventer">
Deventer,
</place>
 
<place id="8669" place_id="Steenwijk">
Steenwicke,
</place>
 
<place id="8672" place_id="Breda">
Breda,
</place>
 
<place id="8675" place_id="Hulst">
Hulst,
</place>
 
<place id="8678" place_id="Steenbergen">
Steenber-
<newline/>
ghen
</place>
, 
<place id="8681" place_id="Groningen">
Groeninghen
</place>
 with other fortes and places of special importance.
<newline/>
Moreover they have had of late yeres a wonderfull augmentation
<newline/>
of their Customes, and talles, by meanes of their fishing, and trafficke
<newline/>
by Sea, which was never soe great as it is at this present, nor this
<newline/>
Contrey was never soe full of inhabitants, nor frequented of forrainers,
<newline/>
soe as hardly howses in most places can by hyred for money.
<newline/>
These were evident and knowen meanes, as there were many more
<newline/>
besydes, to shewe the wealth of these Contreis, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at if the revenues there-
<newline/>
of be not greater then the charges, yet no doubt they are equivalent.
<newline/>
They could not judge otherwise, howsoever some discoursed but
<newline/>
that her Ma
<super id="0316" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 both spake and thought very honorably of their suc-
<newline/>
cors sent for Fraunce. Nevertheles it is a great presumption,
<newline/>
that it comes of great abundance, when any Contrey shall make warre,
<newline/>
<folioref id="0313">
fol.103r
</folioref>
 and winne upon the Enemie, and yet spare of their stoare, to helpe
<newline/>
other Princes. For which her Hig
<super id="0352" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 had good cause after soe
<newline/>
many yeares aide, the consumption of soe much treasure, and the
<newline/>
losse of the lives of soe many of her subjectes, for defence of these
<newline/>
Contreis to calle for restitution. But how muche she would demaunde
<newline/>
to be presently restoared, I could not say upon certaintie, though I
<newline/>
thought it might be lesse, then they peradventure make account.
<newline/>
For so 
<image name="thorn"/>
at order might be taken for good payment heereafter, it
<newline/>
would suffise for the present, by some little good beginning, to
<newline/>
shewe their thanckefull inclination, to give her good satisfaction.
<newline/>
<newline/>
And where they made it a question, whether it were expedient
<newline/>
as their present State staundeth, to imparte soe muche unto 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
people, it did but cary a shewe of a dilatory aunswear. For her
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="0349" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 demande was justly made, and kindly presented, and if the
<newline/>
Deputies of the Provinces would accompanie the same, with suche
<newline/>
kinde of persuasions, as they knewe in their wisdomes how to appropriat,
<newline/>
it would either be accorded, nor nothing ill interpreted.
<newline/>
<newline/>
As concerning those affaires, which Coronel Stewart did negotiat,
<newline/>
it was out of my Comission, to say any thing unto them, and for
<newline/>
ought I could conjecture they were unsignified to her Ma
<super id="0346" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
And therfore if they pleased to accept of my advise as privatly
<newline/>
given, and not otherwise, I know not howe they could doe better,
<newline/>
then to wryte unto her of it, and to crave her good direction:
<newline/>
as alsoe for heereafter, not to deale with that Contrey in any
<newline/>
cause of consequence, but with her Ma
<super id="0384" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 foreknowledge, and with
<newline/>
continual correspondence. My aunswear heerein, and
<newline/>
the rest of my speeches to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e point of restitution, they promised to
<newline/>
signifie in their publicke assemblie: seeming every way to me, to
<newline/>
allowe of my advise, as fitte for them to folowe, for the maters of
<newline/>
Scotland. Coronel Stuart in privat co
<overline id="0364" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
unication,
<newline/>
hath [imparted] me to further his message to the States, declaring
<newline/>
howe neere it concerned her Ma
<super id="0378" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 aswell as the King, and that
<newline/>
questionlesse my service would be gratefull to them both, with other
<newline/>
pertinent inducements. Upon which I inquired, whether the K. had
<newline/>
imparted 
<image name="thorn"/>
at matter to her Ma
<super id="0375" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
. His aunswear was that her
<newline/>
Hig
<super id="0381" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
 was acquainted with the State of the King, and saw he should
<newline/>
be forced to crave the aide of his friendes, for which shee could
<newline/>
<folioref id="0387">
fol.103v
</folioref>
 not but allowe of his proposall to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e States. But yet otherwise alsoe
<newline/>
he thought that shee knew it longe agoe. Whereunto I replied, that
<newline/>
I was sure shee had notice of his publicke employment, before I came
<newline/>
out of England, but I did verilie beleeve 
<image name="thorn"/>
at his errand to this
<newline/>
people was unknowen to her Hig
<super id="0416" replace="hnes">
es
</super>
. Howsoever it were not having
<newline/>
had in charge to deale in his affaires, I was to pray him to excuse
<newline/>
me, if I were not very forward, onely this I would promise, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at
<newline/>
if the States by waye of talke shuld happen to aske me, I would
<newline/>
wishe them to wryte and take advise of her Ma
<super id="0413" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
, and that for
<newline/>
many respectes: but most of all to prevent misconstructions and
<newline/>
jalousies. For he knew well enough that neighbo
<super id="0419" replace="">
rs
</super>
 Princes
<newline/>
though they live in good amitie, will conceave a litle jalousie of
<newline/>
one anothers actions: and whether her Ma
<super id="0410" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 nowe in this p
<overline id="0453" replace="resent">
nt
</overline>
<newline/>
case, all kinde of circumstances weighed (w
<super id="0407" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I would leave to his
<newline/>
discretion to examine throughly) might not thinck somewhat
<newline/>
strange of the K. proceedinges, and more peradventure of the
<newline/>
States, if they should yelde to his demandes, and never aske any
<newline/>
question of her Ma
<super id="0431" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 liking, he himself might be judge.
<newline/>
<newline/>
As for me my endevo
<super id="0428" replace="">
rs
</super>
 should tend to doe good offices, and there could
<newline/>
not be a better, to my little insight, then to minister all occasions
<newline/>
of mutuall intelligence, between her Ma
<super id="0449" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 and them, and the
<newline/>
States of these Contreis. I can not tell very well how he lyked
<newline/>
of my counsaile, but yet my thought but indifferently. Never-
<newline/>
theles he bare me in hand, that both it pleased him well, and h
e
<newline/>
would presently dispatche to moove the King and the Chauncelo
<super id="0446" replace="">
r
</super>
,
<newline/>
to addresse to 
<image name="thorn"/>
at effect some lres to her Ma
<super id="0443" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
, which he also affir-
<newline/>
med to be requyred by the States, whose remonstrance unto him
<newline/>
as chiefly directed, to shewe how muche it would please the gene-
<newline/>
ralitie heere, to understand that the King would frame himself in
<newline/>
all his purposes, to give her Ma
<super id="0470" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 good contentment.
<newline/>
<newline/>
I had this talke with Co. Stuart somwhat after that I had spoken
<newline/>
with those 
<image name="thorn"/>
at were sent from 
<image name="thorn"/>
e States unto me: who as I am persua-
<newline/>
ded told him presently upon it, what I had signified unto them,
<newline/>
with such token of approbation, as it caused him the sooner to
<newline/>
yeeld to me in my former speeche. being asked sins of a 
<newline/>
freend, how he went forward with his suite, he said he could not
<newline/>
<folioref id="0467">
fol.104r
</folioref>
 tell, for that he found himself crossed, whether he meant it
<newline/>
of me, I am not certaine, but I suspect it by dyvers conjectures/
<newline/>
<newline/>
I am told by some about him, 
<image name="thorn"/>
at he hath promised to bring
<newline/>
ten thousand Scottes, to serve against the Turke, if the
<newline/>
Princes of 
<place id="8685" place_id="Germany">
Germanie
</place>
 will give him intertainment, for which
<newline/>
he and his frindes are earnest sollictors: and as I am info
<insertion id="0480">
r
</insertion>
med
<newline/>
have a graunt in a maner, soe that nowe he doth but treate
<newline/>
about the assurance of his pay, for which he requyreth bondes of
<newline/>
some of the Hanse townes. Of the death of 
<person id="8688" person_id="Ernestus">
Ernestus
</person>
<newline/>
I thinke your L. hath notice, and had it assoone, as we in this
<newline/>
place, because our first intelligence came by l
<overline id="0491" replace="ettres">
res
</overline>
 out of 
<place id="8691" place_id="Zeland">
Zeland.
</place>
<newline/>
<newline/>
It giveth occasion of much discoursing, whether every
<newline/>
thing considered, it will proove beneficiall or hurtfull to this
<newline/>
Contrey. But the most are glad of it, and they take it for
<newline/>
a blessing. The rather, for that it comes in a tyme, when the
<newline/>
mutined Italians are discontented a freshe, and others sins
<newline/>
have begonne to folowe their example, in dyvers places of the
<newline/>
frontiers; besydes 
<image name="thorn"/>
at every where we heare, that aswell the
<newline/>
Commons, as nobilitie, were never more distasted of the Spanish
<newline/>
government. Such opportunities as these are not offered often-
<newline/>
tymes, to ruine downe right such an Enemie as 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Spaniard:
<newline/>
and if 
<image name="thorn"/>
e power of this people were but halfe soe muche more
<newline/>
as it is at this p
<overline id="0516" replace="resent">
nt
</overline>
, they would thincke to effect it in very
<newline/>
short tyme. That which I advertised in my laste to
<newline/>
yo
<super id="0513" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. of the carriage of mony out of Zeland into Scotland
<newline/>
was signified unto me by one of the States: but requiring of
<newline/>
it sins, it hath bin told me by others, that the mony was
<newline/>
taken upon royals of plate, by the Marchants of the Minte,
<newline/>
to whome the minting of mony is farmed in Scotland, and
<newline/>
that it was for their owne use. 
<section id="0533" Section="subscription" Place="none">
And thus excusing my
<newline/>
lenght with the occasions presented, and beseeching your L.
<newline/>
to make reporte unto her Ma
<super id="0530" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 of as muche as is convenient,
<newline/>
I take my humble leave./. Fe
<abbreviation id="0527" replace="bruary">
b
</abbreviation>
 22.
</section>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
