<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="1335">
<folioref id="1272">
fol.275r
</folioref>
 
<section id="1281" Section="lateraddition" Place="top_left">
18 Novem
<abbreviation id="1278" replace="ber">
b
</abbreviation>
 To M
<super id="1275" replace="aster">
r
</super>
 Bodly
</section>
<newline/>
<section id="1288" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
Belgia: 1591. No
<abbreviation id="1285" replace="vember">
v
</abbreviation>
</section>
<newline/>
After my very harty commendations. Whearas the Company of the
<newline/>
<person id="5850" person_id="Merchant Adventurers">
Marchants Adventurers
</person>
 have infourmed us hear of a certein Placard
<newline/>
lately published by the 
<person id="5853" person_id="States General">
States
</person>
 of the 
<place id="5856" place_id="United Provinces">
united Provinces
</place>
, as touching
<newline/>
the taring or rebating of the prizes of the English cloth, and a niew
<newline/>
impost stayed upon the same: Whearunto the sayed Marchants have
<newline/>
made their exceptions in writing, and sent them over to bee perused
<newline/>
and considered of by the sayed States: forasmuche as the sayed taring
<newline/>
of the English cloth, with the sayed niew imposition, will bee very
<newline/>
prejudiciall, not only to the Marchants themselves, and their trade thear,
<newline/>
but also to the 
<person id="5859" person_id="Elizabeth">
Queenes
</person>
 coustooms, and the whole drapery of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Realm,
<newline/>
in case it should proceed, as (it seemeth), is intended by the sayed
<newline/>
States: These ar to desier you to infourm yo
<super id="1304" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 self of the state and
<newline/>
particulars of the cause, and of the reasons alleadged by the Marchant
<image name="es"/>
<newline/>
Adventurers against the sayed Placard, and niew imposition, whearof
<newline/>
(as I understand by them) they have sent you a copie both in Latin and
<newline/>
English and to prosequute the same for them as in her Ma
<super id="1312" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 name
<newline/>
to the best effect you can. Whearin you shall doe very good service
<newline/>
not only to them, but to the Queen hir self, and the whole Realm. 
<section id="1332" Section="subscription" Place="none">
And
<newline/>
thus I bidd you hartily to farewell. From the Court the 18
<super id="1318" replace="">
th
</super>
 of 
<newline/>
November 
<underline id="1322">
1591
</underline>
.
<newline/>
Yo
<super id="1329" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 very loving friend 
<hand id="1326" type="Burghley" Description="">
William Burghley
</hand>
</section>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
