<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="1531">
<folioref id="0766">
fol.192r
</folioref>
 
<section id="0775" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
Novem
<linethrough id="0769" replace="ber">
b
</linethrough>
 1591 33 Eli
<abbreviation id="0772" replace="zabeth">
z
</abbreviation>
 Netherlands
</section>
<newline/>
<section id="0786" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
It seemes this Letter was never sent. see back side
<newline/>
w
<super id="0780" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 seemes to bee S
<super id="0783" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Thomas Bodleys own hand.
</section>
<newline/>
Having lately understoode, aswell by those letters w
<super id="0790" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 yow have written
<newline/>
to the states, and to yo
<super id="0794" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 frindes in these countreis, as by divers other
<newline/>
meanes of assured intelligence, that yow determine very shortly to ad-
<newline/>
dresse yo
<super id="0802" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 selves to the forsaide 
<person id="3264" person_id="States General">
states
</person>
 and in the name of the 
<person id="3258" person_id="Rudolf II">
Empero
<super id="0799" replace="">
rs
</super>
</person>
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="0806" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 to motion some agreement between them and the Spaniard,
<newline/>
I have thought it very requisit for discharge of my dewtie to my
<newline/>
Souveraigne lady and mistresse the 
<person id="3267" person_id="Elizabeth">
Q. Ma
<super id="0812" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
</person>
 of 
<place id="3270" place_id="England">
England,
</place>
 who hath
<newline/>
bin pleased to honour me, w
<super id="0816" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the place of her Counsailo
<super id="0819" replace="">
r
</super>
 in this 
<person id="3273" person_id="Council of State">
Co
<overline id="0822" replace="un">
u
</overline>
cel
<newline/>
of state
</person>
, and for those principal respects, w
<super id="0827" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I beare in all humilitie
<newline/>
to the Empero
<super id="0831" replace="">
rs
</super>
 Ma
<super id="0834" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 between whom and my Souveraigne all offices
<newline/>
of amitie have bin alwaies intertened, to prevent yo
<super id="0838" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 comming hither
<newline/>
w
<super id="0842" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 such advise as this place, and my function will affourd.
<newline/>
<newline/>
It is ten moneths agoe 
<image name="thorn"/>
at 
<image name="thorn"/>
e states of these countreis, upon advertisment
<newline/>
receaved of yo
<super id="0850" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 purposed voiage then, to the like effect as nowe, for the
<newline/>
advancement of a peace, directed presently their letters, both to the
<newline/>
Empero
<super id="0858" replace="">
rs
</super>
 Ma
<super id="0855" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 and to certaine Princes of the Empire, to the end they
<newline/>
should surcease from poursuing that intent; for that it tended altoge-
<newline/>
ther, as was effectually declared, to the ruine of their state, and to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
Enemies sole advantage. It was hoped therupon that the reasons
<newline/>
then alleaged, w
<super id="0866" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 made a plaine demonstration of many daungerous
<newline/>
inconveniences, that were like to growe upon it, had dissuaded his Ma
<super id="0870" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
from following his designe. But forasmuche as that hope is altogether
<newline/>
frustrat, to the exceeding great griefe of the foresaide states, and of
<newline/>
as many heere, or wheresoever as are ether embarked in the self same
<newline/>
cause, or perfitly acquainted w
<super id="0877" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the state of their affaires, I doubt not
<newline/>
but 
<image name="thorn"/>
at they of themselves will be as carefull, as is possible, to forecast
<newline/>
the very woorst, that they may not be surprised by the glavering offers
<newline/>
of the Enemie. Nevertheles for the readier prevention of all that
<newline/>
may happen, and for the better acquitting of my charge and duty
<newline/>
to my Souveraigne, I am to signifie more unto yow, concerning this
<newline/>
treaty w
<super id="0887" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 yow purpose to negotiat, then hath bin happely expressed
<newline/>
in any letter of the states, or otherwise imparted to the Emperors
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="0895" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 and to yow. What it was that moved the Q. Ma
<super id="0892" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
of England, to undertake the protection and defence of these Provinces,
<newline/>
<folioref id="0900">
fol.192v
</folioref>
 
<section id="0903" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
November 1591
</section>
<newline/>
I thinke there is no doubt, but that 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Empero
<super id="0908" replace="">
rs
</super>
 Ma
<super id="0911" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 doth knowe sufficiently
<newline/>
and according to his wisdome doth approve her proceeding. For she hath
<newline/>
not dealt in secret and covertly, but proceeded w
<super id="0916" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 all integritie, and by
<newline/>
publicke declaration, in w
<super id="0920" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 her reasons are proposed to the censure 
<newline/>
of all the worlde. But what passed in accorde between her Ma
<super id="0924" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
and this people, and in what conditions ether partie is subject unto
<newline/>
other, that is it w
<super id="0936" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I suppose is wholy unknowen to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Empero
<super id="0933" replace="">
rs
</super>
 Ma
<super id="0930" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
and to yow, or not so knowen in every point, as hath bin solemnely by
<newline/>
them, and reciprocally contracted. It may therfore please yow
<newline/>
to be informed, that among other articles and couvenants it is a spe-
<newline/>
cial point agreed, that nether the General nor Particular states
<newline/>
of these provinces, shall enter into treaty w
<super id="0944" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the common Enemie
<newline/>
<image name="thorn"/>
e Spaniard, nor w
<super id="0950" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 any Prince or Potentat in his behalf, w
<super id="0953" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
privitie and assent of the Q. Ma
<super id="0957" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 of England. And to as many as
<newline/>
are heere of her Ma
<super id="0963" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 ministers, be they Gouvernors of townes, com-
<newline/>
maunders in the feelde, or other officers of trust, there is nothing re-
<newline/>
commended more precisely to their charge, nor more effectually
<newline/>
sett downe in the othe w
<super id="2463" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they have taken to their Souvraigne and
<newline/>
this contrey, then 
<image name="thorn"/>
at they shall observe, and cause to be observed to their
<newline/>
uttermost endevo
<super id="0974" replace="">
r
</super>
, the forsaide article of the Treaty. By
<newline/>
vertue wherof I doe declare by these presents, and notifie unto yow,
<newline/>
that wee are all of us determined to discharge the services of credit
<newline/>
committed heere 
<overline id="0980" replace="un">
u
</overline>
to us. And though wee knowe there is no doubt,
<newline/>
but that the states of these contreis doe finde their owne prospe-
<newline/>
ritie, and can see the afflicted state of those Provinces and towns,
<newline/>
that are not of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e union: for w
<super id="0987" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 it is to be presumed, that they will
<newline/>
not disesteeme, 
<underline id="0991">
or not
</underline>
 
<insertion id="0994">
but
</insertion>
 sufficiently esteeme those extraordinary graces,
<newline/>
w
<super id="0998" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 w
<super id="1001" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 God hath so often, and nowe so very lately, blessed their ex-
<newline/>
ploites: but rather will goe forewarde w
<super id="1008" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 a greater courrage aga
<overline id="1005" replace="in">
i
</overline>
st
<newline/>
the Enemie, both assaulting him by force, and impeaching his un-
<newline/>
just 
<overline id="1013" replace="an">
a
</overline>
d fraudulent designes. Nevertheles, as if wee knewe
<newline/>
not that intention of the foresaide states, we are thus muche of
<newline/>
o
<super id="1018" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 selves to signifie from hens, that unles yow come autorised to this
<newline/>
treaty of peace w
<super id="1025" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the allowance and warrant of the Q. o
<super id="1022" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 Mistresse
<newline/>
<folioref id="1029">
fol.193r
</folioref>
 
<section id="1032" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
November 1591
</section>
<newline/>
we must all in general, and every one in particular stand against yow, not
<newline/>
only w
<super id="1041" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 good arguments of reason and persuasion, but w
<super id="1038" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 all the meanes 
<image name="thorn"/>
at
<newline/>
we can make, by any violence or force to disturbe yo
<super id="1046" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 attempts: and 
<image name="thorn"/>
at
<newline/>
w
<super id="1050" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out attending or expecting w
<super id="1053" replace="hat">
at
</super>
 the Contrey shall resolve. This
<newline/>
message, I knowe, may seeme unto yow straunge, considering that 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
intention of the Emperor tendeth onely to a Concorde, w
<super id="1059" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 is a mat
<newline/>
ter well worthy of his wisdome and puissance, and a thing to be
<newline/>
embraced of every good Christian. But suche is the bonde
<newline/>
of o
<super id="1068" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 alleageance to o
<super id="1071" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 Souveraigne, the importance of o
<super id="1065" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 othes in
<newline/>
respect of the Contract, and o
<super id="1075" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 duties, in general to the cause of
<newline/>
these contreis, that w
<super id="1079" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out o
<super id="2466" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 Princes dispensation, we may not swarve
<newline/>
from this course, w
<super id="1083" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I have signified heere unto yowe. Nevertheles,
<newline/>
to say somewhat to the mater, for w
<super id="1087" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 yo
<super id="1090" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 comming is intended, albeit
<newline/>
it is not my principal purpose, nor a subject to be handled in so
<newline/>
short a letter, yet 
<image name="thorn"/>
e cause being general and yow indifferently
<newline/>
affected, to make a fruitfull composition, and that w
<super id="1097" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out any pre-
<newline/>
judice to one side or other, upon this oportunitie of writing unto
<newline/>
yow, I hope yow will vouchesafe to consider upon the growndes, for
<newline/>
w
<super id="1104" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 this people will refuse to come in treaty w
<super id="1107" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Spaniard.
<newline/>
First they say, It is certaine, whatseover is averred by any to the
<newline/>
contrary, that 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 
<person id="3276" person_id="Phillip II">
King of Spaines
</person>
 disposition is wholy opposit to peace.
<newline/>
And this is proved apparantly by a common observation, w
<super id="1114" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 is in
<newline/>
every mans discourse, that there is noe warre at this day in any part
<newline/>
of Christendome but is directly or indirectly sturred and maintained
<newline/>
by the K. of Spaine. What example can be plainer, then his present
<newline/>
partaking in the kingdome of 
<place id="3279" place_id="France">
France?
</place>
 where w
<super id="1121" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out a just occasi-
<newline/>
on 
<insertion id="1125">
or
</insertion>
 pretext of just occasion, he endevoureth to depose the right ow-
<newline/>
ner from his scepter, and all under collo
<super id="1130" replace="">
r
</super>
 of zele and divotion to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
Romishe religion. And if that be all his cause, as his pretence is
<newline/>
no other, would the Emperors Ma
<super id="3282" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 have this people to imagine,
<newline/>
that the kinge of Spaine can be pleased, to permitte unto them,
<newline/>
over whome he clameth a right and absolut autoritie the use of 
<image name="thorn"/>
at
<newline/>
religion for the extirpation wherof he poursueth a forraine Prince
<newline/>
w
<super id="1145" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 all 
<image name="thorn"/>
e actes of hostilitie, that he can possibly practise? His purpose
<newline/>
<folioref id="1142">
fol.193v
</folioref>
 
<section id="1148" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
November 1591
</section>
<newline/>
is too manifest: he mindes to make holy day w
<super id="1153" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e states of these contreis, till his
<newline/>
maters in France succeede to his minde, and then his hope is, undoubtedly,
<newline/>
that not onely these 
<place id="3285" place_id="United Provinces">
Provinces united
</place>
, but England and 
<place id="3288" place_id="Scotland">
Scotland,
</place>
 and
<newline/>
every part of 
<place id="3291" place_id="Germany">
Germany,
</place>
 or of any other contrey, that is different from
<newline/>
him in religion, or disjoined in faction, shall accept of suche lawes as he for
<newline/>
his benefit shall prescribe unto them. But let it be admitted,
<newline/>
that his desire to be at peace, is in deede so sincere, as all men knowe
<newline/>
it is dissembled, It is not integrum no more to the people of this contrey,
<newline/>
to condiscend to his demaunde. For their obedience unto him was reno
<overline id="1165" replace="un">
u
</overline>
-
<newline/>
ced long agoe, as to a most cruel and unaturall Tyranne: for w
<super id="1168" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they so-
<newline/>
lemnly proceeded to a publicke Abjuration, by a special forme of wordes:
<newline/>
w
<super id="1174" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 not onely the Magistrats and officers of every towne but every one
<newline/>
in a manner of the meanest of the people hath vowed to observe. And
<newline/>
their vowes to that effect have bin continually confirmed, w
<super id="1177" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 as many let-
<newline/>
ters and bookes, and publicke Actes, as have bin published ever sins.
<newline/>
Besides as I have shewed, they are bounde by a special league to her Ma
<super id="1182" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
of England, the onely Prince in Christendome that hath protected their
<newline/>
estate w
<super id="1187" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the daunger of her owne, not to deale in any motion for accord-
<newline/>
ing w
<super id="1191" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the Enemie, w
<super id="1194" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out her notice and avowe. And for her better
<newline/>
assurance, as well of that as of other conditions, they have put in to her
<newline/>
custody in lieu of caution and pledges, such places for townes, as there
<newline/>
are not any belonginge to the states of these contreis of greater import
<overline id="1200" replace="an">
a
</overline>
ce
<newline/>
Whiche if her Ma
<super id="1204" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 should convert to their uttermost annoiance, pro-
<newline/>
voked therunto by the infraction of their pactes, no doubt their forces are
<newline/>
so slender, that their present florishing state would quickly come to
<newline/>
ruine. There is also this to be considered, that seing the 
<person id="3295" person_id="Navarre">
Frenche King
</person>
<newline/>
is notoriously wronged by 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Spaniardes oppression, and is lincked to this
<newline/>
nation in the qualitie of his cause, and they have hitherto assisted him
<newline/>
w
<super id="1214" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 suche reliefe as their state is able to affourde, it can not any way
<newline/>
concurre w
<super id="1219" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e honor of their actions, besides the multitude of perils
<newline/>
to w
<super id="1226" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they may be subejct, to assent to any peace, w
<super id="1223" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out his special ap-
<newline/>
probation. But to suppose, if yow please, that they may, if
<newline/>
they list, growe in amitie w
<super id="1234" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the Enemie and may revoke w
<super id="1231" replace="hat">
at
</super>
soever they
<newline/>
formerly done, or contracted to the contrary, and that w
<super id="1238" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out any prejudice
<newline/>
to themselves or to their neighbo
<super id="1242" replace="">
rs
</super>
, yet this were nothing to these contreis,
<newline/>
to make them hearcken to a peace. For not onely the better sort heere,
<newline/>
<catchword id="1251">
and such 
</catchword>
<newline/>
<section id="1248" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
vid. supra fol. 190
</section>
<newline/>
<folioref id="1255">
fol.190r
</folioref>
 
<section id="1258" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
November 1591
</section>
<newline/>
<section id="1263" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
vid infra, fol.192
</section>
<newline/>
and suche as are most conversant in the affaires of their gouvernment but every
<newline/>
simple person of vulgar understanding can lay before you many reasons and
<newline/>
can make it evident by proofes that are familiar to all the worlde, that there
<newline/>
can be no Assurance in any peace w
<super id="1270" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Spaniard. They have alwaies obser-
<newline/>
ved, and doe observe every day by their owne experience, and by the examples
<newline/>
of others, by 
<image name="thorn"/>
e letters of advise, w
<super id="1276" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they have taken of the kinge and by all
<newline/>
his proceedinges w
<super id="1280" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 them and w
<super id="1283" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 others, that all his promises and proposals
<newline/>
are captious and counterfaict, tending onely to entrappe and to gaine a littel
<newline/>
time, that by abusing their credulitie, he may watche a fitte occasion to
<newline/>
be revenged upon them. This they have tried in former times by the trea-
<newline/>
cherous Treaties of 
<place id="3298" place_id="Breda">
Breda,
</place>
 of Marche in Famine and of 
<place id="3301" place_id="Collen">
Collen,
</place>
 of w
<super id="1290" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
<newline/>
and other like the memorie w
<super id="1294" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 them is so freshe, and the dommages so great
<newline/>
w
<super id="1306" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they have sustened by 
<image name="thorn"/>
e losse of divers townes and Provinces, and by the
<newline/>
daungerous alterations, w
<super id="1300" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 the Enemie w
<super id="1303" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 his cunning sette a foote among
<newline/>
the Commons, as if they trust him any more, they might seeme to be be-
<newline/>
refte of all goode use of common sense. But besides the examples among
<newline/>
themselves, they sawe the other day in his dealing w
<super id="1312" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 England a most
<newline/>
palpable patterne of Spanishe falshoode and deceat. For even then, and
<newline/>
at the same instant, that his ministers were emploied to persuade her Ma
<super id="1317" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
to a peace, by proposing unto her very plausible conditions, he armed a Navy
<newline/>
to the seas, w
<super id="1323" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 in his Lucifers pride he termed Invincible, to make a conquest
<newline/>
of her kingdome. But howe that wickednes was punished by 
<image name="thorn"/>
e mightie
<newline/>
hand of God, it is knowen er this to all the worlde, and it will be recorded to
<newline/>
all posteritie. Againe by Gods good providence they have had the hap-
<newline/>
pines of late to intercept certaine letters subscribed w
<super id="1330" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the Kinges owne hande
<newline/>
and addressed to 
<person id="3304" person_id="St Clement">
Don Guillaume de S
<super id="1334" replace="">
t
</super>
 Clement
</person>
 his owne Ambassador in
<newline/>
the Emperors court, by w
<super id="1338" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 it doth appeare, that howsoever his offers are outwardly
<newline/>
disguised w
<super id="1342" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the cloake of Pacification, the secret drift of his hearte, and his
<newline/>
inward intention is full of malice and imposture. In effect all his actions
<newline/>
are directed by that most unchristian, and barbarous maxime, That w
<super id="1347" replace="ith">
t
</super>
<newline/>
an Hereticke there is no faith to be observed. Whiche infamous point
<newline/>
of doctrine was most wickedly devised by the 
<person id="3307" person_id="Gregory, Pope">
Pope
</person>
 and Popishe Princes, to
<newline/>
serve their wordly turnes: distrusting as it seemeth the truth of their owne
<newline/>
Religion, As if God were not able, their cause being just, (as they are per-
<newline/>
suaded) and their party being greater by many multitudes of people, to
<newline/>
uphold their estate w
<super id="1357" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out 
<image name="thorn"/>
e breache of common faith. But if this be
<newline/>
so maintened against Heretickes in general, w
<super id="1361" replace="hat">
at
</super>
 application will be made
<newline/>
<folioref id="1365">
fol.190v
</folioref>
 
<section id="1371" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
November 1591
</section>
<newline/>
by the king and his favourers against the Heretickes of this contrey? W
<super id="1375" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
<newline/>
have taken armes against him, have renounced his religion, solemnly deposed
<newline/>
him by way of Abjuration, and delivered unto others the possession of his
<newline/>
landes. It is certaine, in conclusion, howsoever all his offers are masqued
<newline/>
w
<super id="1382" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 faire promises, and sette out unto the shewe, they are inwardly full of
<newline/>
guile, and of a daungerous double meaning. But thankes be to God
<newline/>
the people of these Provinces have a special insight in their owne estate,
<newline/>
and give a singular judgement of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e nature of these motives of the Em-
<newline/>
pero
<super id="1394" replace="">
rs
</super>
 Ma
<super id="1391" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
. They have felt so often the smarte of those roddes of the
<newline/>
Spanishe Pacifications that they can rectefie their courses by their
<newline/>
owne experience, wherby they knowe, as I have signified, That first
<newline/>
the Kinge hath no willingnes to estbalishe any peace: secondly that 
<newline/>
it is not in their power to admitte any treaty: and thirdly that they
<newline/>
can have no securitie by any composition. And yet againe to presuppose
<newline/>
that the Kinges intention were entire and unfained, that the contrey
<newline/>
heere were at libertie to make their owne peace, and that 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Kinges
<newline/>
proceedinges had given no occasion to incurre so great suspicion, yet to
<newline/>
returne againe to that w
<super id="1411" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 is the cheifest occasion of my writinge 
<overline id="1408" replace="un">
u
</overline>
to
<newline/>
you, Unles yow shewe for yo
<super id="1415" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 comming the liking and permission of her
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="1419" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 my Souveraigne, I must needes forwarne yow as before, That
<newline/>
as many of us as are heere of her Ma
<super id="1426" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 subjectes, doe resolve to w
<super id="1423" replace="ith">
t
</super>
stand
<newline/>
yow, as perturbers of the amitie between her and the contrey. And
<newline/>
in 
<image name="thorn"/>
at respect every man in his charge will accomplishe the duties of
<newline/>
his faith and obedience, by forcing yow from hens. And though
<newline/>
I speake in this sorte very plainely and roundly, beinge bounde therunto
<newline/>
by mine othe and alleageance, yet I rest out of doubt, that yo
<super id="1435" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 singular
<newline/>
wisdeomes will expounde my meaning to the best, an
d 
being somuche
<newline/>
preadvertised of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e strict alliance and contract between her Ma
<super id="1441" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 and
<newline/>
these contreis, will forbeare upon it to goe forward w
<super id="1448" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 yo
<super id="1445" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 voiage intended.
<newline/>
But if it fall out so in truthe, as in semblance is pretended, that the
<newline/>
Kinge of Spaine ether weried w
<super id="1453" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 his warres, or reduced to extremitie,
<newline/>
or findinge in continuance that God doth not prosper his dissembled
<newline/>
proceedinges, shall be willing now at lenght to speake as he thinketh,
<newline/>
and to stipulat a firme and a durable peace, there is no other kinde of
<newline/>
meanes to effect his purpose, but by causing the like proffers of peace,
<newline/>
as are made to these Provinces, to be presented in like sorte to her Ma
<super id="1461" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 of England
<newline/>
<folioref id="1465">
fol.191r
</folioref>
 
<section id="1468" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
November 1591
</section>
<newline/>
to the Kinge in France, and to as many other Princes as sitte complaininge
<newline/>
at the helme of one common cause, and runne in danger to be drowned
<newline/>
in the bottomlesse gulf of the Spanishe Ambition. To this there
<newline/>
is no doubt but 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Kinge will condiscend, if his minde and meaning be
<newline/>
cleere and upright, and this is it w
<super id="1480" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 her Ma
<super id="1477" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 my Souveraigne, the
<newline/>
states of these contreis, and every forraine Potentat will most wil-
<newline/>
lingly helpe forewarde, w
<super id="1486" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 all the meanes of assistaunce that they can
<newline/>
minister unto him.
<newline/>
<folioref id="1490">
fol.191v
</folioref>
 
<section id="1506" Section="endorsement" Place="none">
Project of a l
<overline id="1500" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
 w
<super id="1503" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I purposed to send to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Empero
<super id="1497" replace="">
rs
</super>
 Ambas
<abbreviation id="1494" replace="sadors">
s
</abbreviation>
</section>
<newline/>
<hand id="1528" type="scribe" Description="">
<section id="1519" Section="endorsement" Place="none">
Thomas Bodley Ambassador w
<super id="1510" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 the States of Holland 
<deletion id="1513">
to the
</deletion>
 the Coppy of his Lettere writen to the Emperores Ambassadores, November 1591 33 Eli
<abbreviation id="1516" replace="zabeth">
z
</abbreviation>
</section>
</hand>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>