<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="0005">
<folioref id="0006">
fol.256r
</folioref>
 
<hand id="0009" type="scribe" Description="">
Dania:
</hand>
 11 August 1588.
<newline/>
A Memoriall for M
<super id="0196" replace="aster">
r
</super>
 Thomas Bodley
<newline/>
sent by her Ma
<super id="0199" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 unto the 
<person id="0188" person_id="Christian IV">
King of
<newline/>
Denmarke
</person>
.
<newline/>
<newline/>
You shall make your present repaire to 
<place id="0192" place_id="Margate">
Margate
</place>
, where
<newline/>
by vertue of our letters unto the 
<person id="0197" person_id="Lord Admiral Howard">
L. Admirall
</person>
, or in his
<newline/>
absence to the Vice Admirall you shalbe furnished with
<newline/>
shipping for your transportation.
<newline/>
<newline/>
And after you shalbe embarqued you shall carefully by the
<newline/>
way informe your selfe by such shippes, as you shall meet
<newline/>
comming from the Eastparts, what is become of the
<newline/>
Spannish Fleete, and if you shall understand that
<newline/>
the Fleete is repaired towards 
<place id="0201" place_id="Hamburg">
Hamborough
</place>
, and
<newline/>
shall use the best and most forcible reasons you may
<newline/>
to persuade those of Hamborough not victuall or
<newline/>
any waie to relieve the Spanyard the Common enemie
<newline/>
of the Christian Religion, and shall for that purpose
<newline/>
putt them in mind, how the Spannish Nation sought in
<newline/>
<person id="0204" person_id="Charles V">
Charles the Emperors
</person>
 time to make a Conquest of 
<place id="0207" place_id="Germany">
Ger-
<newline/>
many
</place>
, and for your better creditt you shall deliver her
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="0035" replace="jesties">
tes
</super>
 letters to those of Hamborough.
<newline/>
<newline/>
And in case you shall understand that the Fleetes are
<newline/>
passed further Eastward, then you shall repaire to 
<place id="0210" place_id="Denmark">
Den-
<newline/>
marke
</place>
, and there by vertue of her Ma
<super id="0049" replace="jesties">
tes
</super>
 letter directed
<newline/>
both to the King, and the Gouvernors of that Realme, you
<newline/>
shall sollicite the said King and Gouvernors to forbeare
<newline/>
to yeald reliefe to the Spaniards. And to induce them
<newline/>
the better to give ease thereunto, you shall acquainte
<newline/>
the said King and Gouvenors, how the 
<person id="0213" person_id="Parma, A">
Duke of Parma
</person>
<newline/>
hath only used a colour of Treaty to abuse her Ma
<super id="0052" replace="jestie">
te
</super>
<newline/>
minding an [i
<overline id="0060" replace="nter">
n
</overline>
ceasion], as by the manner of proceeding
<newline/>
appeareth, wherin the honor of the 
<person id="0216" person_id="Frederick II">
late King of Den-
<newline/>
marke
</person>
 is touched, who first motioned the matter unto
<newline/>
her Ma
<super id="0120" replace="jestie">
te
</super>
 whom they likewise thought to have abused
<newline/>
in seeking to perswade him to be an intercessor towards
<newline/>
her Ma
<super id="0117" replace="jestie">
te
</super>
, thereby to have bredd in her a carelesse secu-
<newline/>
rity with the hazard of h
er Estate.
<newline/>
<newline/>
You shall putt the King and the said Gouvernors in
<newline/>
mind of the honorable offer made by the late King unto
<newline/>
her Ma
<super id="0114" replace="jestie">
te
</super>
 that if her Ma
<super id="0111" replace="jestie">
te
</super>
 or her Realme should be
<newline/>
assailed, he 
<deletion id="0070">
[come]
</deletion>
 would come to assist her in person.
<newline/>
You shall lett them understand that the cause is ge-
<newline/>
nerall to all making profession of Religion, the 
<person id="0219" person_id="Sixtus, Pope">
Pope
</person>
<newline/>
being declared the head of this warre, and undoubtedly
<newline/>
to ayde those, which pretend title to the Kingdom of
<newline/>
Denmark as the house of Lorraine, who depend uppon
<newline/>
<place id="0222" place_id="Spain">
Spaine
</place>
, and are the cause of the troubles now in 
<place id="0225" place_id="France">
France
</place>
.
<newline/>
<newline/>
You shall lett them know that the conspiracy hath a
<newline/>
further reach to deprive the protestant Princes of
<newline/>
Germany of such Estates, Bishopricks, and livings,
<newline/>
which they nowe hold, and bestowe them uppon such others
<newline/>
as are addicted unto them. And also you shall advise
<newline/>
the said K. and Gouvernors not to believe their faire
<newline/>
wordes, and promises, seeing so ill deedes.
<newline/>
<folioref id="0088">
fol.256v
</folioref>
 
<hand id="0091" type="scribe" Description="">
Dania: 1588 
<abbreviation id="3664" replace="August">
Aug
</abbreviation>
:
</hand>
<newline/>
You shall so soone as you can gett knowledge where
<newline/>
the Spannish Fleet shall resorte to be relieved of his
<newline/>
Wants, enforme your selfe in what State the said
<newline/>
shipps are, what be their wants, how many in nom-
<newline/>
ber, what sicknes there is among them, and what
<newline/>
persons of quality they have lost in the last fights
<newline/>
had with her Ma
<super id="0108" replace="jesties">
tes
</super>
 navye, or otherwise by sicknes,
<newline/>
what favor they receive in places, where you shall
<newline/>
find them, and from whom, and which way they
<newline/>
meane to returne either 
<deletion id="0105">
through
</deletion>
 to the west
<newline/>
through the Narrow Seas betwixt 
<place id="0228" place_id="England">
England
</place>
 and
<newline/>
France, or about by the west of 
<place id="0234" place_id="Scotland">
Scotland
</place>
, or by 
<place id="0237" place_id="Ireland">
Ire-
<newline/>
land
</place>
, of all which particularities so soone as you
<newline/>
shalbe thoroughly informed, you shall advertise us
<newline/>
by the barke that is appointed to goe with you.
<newline/>
And in case you shall learne that any of the
<newline/>
<place id="0252" place_id="Hanse Towns">
Hanze Townes
</place>
 shall send any reliefe of victuals
<newline/>
or munition to the said Spanyards, you shall then
<newline/>
deale with the Gouvernors of Denmarke to move
<newline/>
them to use some meanes towards the said
<newline/>
Townes to disswade them from yeelding them any
<newline/>
such reliefe, and besides you shall lett fall some
<newline/>
speeches in such sort, as the same may be reported
<newline/>
unto those of the Hanze Townes, that in case
<newline/>
any such reliefe shalbe yeelded unto them, such
<newline/>
of her Ma
<super id="0143" replace="jesties">
tes
</super>
 subjects, as shall serve on the seas,
<newline/>
shalbe justly provoked to take revenge of such shipps
<newline/>
as shall belong to the said Townes, considering the
<newline/>
said Spanyards have their purpose by such ayde
<newline/>
to invade this Realme with a mind of a conquest.
<newline/>
And in case you shall find 
<person id="0240" person_id="Rogers, D">
M
<super id="0193" replace="aster">
r
</super>
 Daniell Rogers
</person>
 in
<newline/>
Denmarke, you shall then acquainte him with this
<newline/>
your charge, and require his assistance and advise
<newline/>
therein by whom you shall enforme your selfe, whether
<newline/>
according to the direction given him he did acquaint
<newline/>
the Gouvernors of Denmark with a practise the
<newline/>
Duke of Parmas uppon an Iland lying uppon
<newline/>
the Coast of 
<place id="0246" place_id="Norway">
Norway
</place>
 called 
<place id="0249" place_id="Ilekewe">
Ilekewe
</place>
, nere to a
<newline/>
Towne called 
<place id="0243" place_id="Otterness">
Otterness
</place>
, whereof he was directed to lett
<newline/>
the said Gouvernors understand, that the said Duke
<newline/>
seeketh the possession to the end he may be the
<newline/>
better able to stoppe the navigation of the Holland
<newline/>
and others into the Sound, which if he should bring
<newline/>
to passe, would prove merveilous prejudiciall to
<newline/>
that Realme, and therefore in case the said Rogers
<newline/>
shalbe departed before your arrivall there, you
<newline/>
shall notwithstanding acquainte them with the
<newline/>
said practice.
<newline/>
Lastly 
<block id="0166" Box="None" Position="Left" Direction="horizontal">
if by the waye you have
<newline/>
certaine intelligence
</block>
 that the said Fleete hath taken the way
<newline/>
about Scottland, or shall happen to returne hether
<newline/>
<catchword id="0171">
wards
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0178">
fol.257r
</folioref>
 
<hand id="0182" type="scribe" Description="">
Dania: 1588 
<abbreviation id="3667" replace="August">
Aug
</abbreviation>
:
</hand>
<newline/>
 hetherwards to passe thorough the narrow Seas so
<newline/>
as it is not likely the same shall repaire to any of
<newline/>
the said Kings Dominions, or the territories of any of
<newline/>
the steeds, then you shall not need to proceede any
<newline/>
further in your voyage, but returne againe hether-
<newline/>
wards.
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
