<transcript>
<page num="1">
<addressleaf id="0500">
<folioref id="0009">
fol.268r
</folioref>
<section id="0012" Section="endorsement" Place="none">
Memoriall from my LL.
</section>
 
<section id="0015" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
Belgia. 1588 23 Novemb
<missing id="0404" type="cut">
er
</missing>
</section>
</addressleaf>
<lettertext id="0501">
<folioref id="0022">
fol.269r
</folioref>
 
<section id="0028" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
23 November 1588. At Somerset howse.
</section>
<newline/>
Memoriall for Thomas Bodley Esquier, being sent
<newline/>
into the 
<place id="0418" place_id="Low Countries">
Lowe Contryes
</place>
 to resyde there as Counsailor
<newline/>
of State.
<newline/>
<newline/>
1. Whereas there were presented unto her 
<person id="0422" person_id="Elizabeth">
Ma
<super id="0036" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
</person>
 in Februarie Last certaine
<newline/>
Requestes on the Behalfe of the 
<person id="0430" person_id="States General">
States generall
</person>
 of the unyted Provinces
<newline/>
by 
<person id="0426" person_id="Ortell, J">
m
<super id="0042" replace="aster">
r
</super>
 Ortell
</person>
 theire Agent, whereunto by her Ma
<super id="0039" replace="jesties">
tes
</super>
 especiall direction
<newline/>
there was 
<image name="par"/>
ticuler answer made by us unto theire severall requestes
<newline/>
wherew
<super id="0053" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 the States doe not rest satysfied: It ys thought meete for
<newline/>
that 
<person id="0434" person_id="Norris, J">
S
<super id="0050" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 John Norris
</person>
 was directed by her Ma
<super id="0056" replace="jesties">
tes
</super>
 Instructions given
<newline/>
unto him, to let the States understand that they should receave further
<newline/>
answer touchinge the said requestes by yo
<super id="4852" replace="">
w
</super>
 that yo
<super id="0442" replace="">
w
</super>
 should goe thorowlie
<newline/>
instructed howe to answer the same, in soche sorte as they ought
<newline/>
in reason to rest satysfied w
<super id="0070" replace="ith">
th
</super>
all
<newline/>
<newline/>
2 First the matter of service monie, as for turfe, candles, and other
<newline/>
allowaunce w
<super id="0077" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 hathe by them ben furnished unto the extraordinarie
<newline/>
Bands garrysioned in the two Cautyonarie Townes, for w
<super id="0080" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they
<newline/>
desier that paiment maie be made unto them and soche order to be taken
<newline/>
as they maie be eased hereafter of these chardges for that they fall out
<newline/>
(By reason of these extraordinarie nombers) to be more chardgable
<newline/>
unto them as they alleadge, then the whole paie was wonte to ryse
<newline/>
unto when they kept the said townes in theire owne handes; w
<super id="0083" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 a
<newline/>
further request also that they maie be allowed soche sommes of money
<newline/>
as they have dysboursed bothe to the said Garrysons and other her
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="0094" replace="jesties">
tes
</super>
 subjectes servinge in those Countries. For the firste touchinge
<newline/>
the service m
<overline id="0417" replace="on">
o
</overline>
nie, yo
<super id="0436" replace="">
w
</super>
 shall let them understand that for as moche as
<newline/>
those extraordynarie bands so placed in the Cawtionary townes beinge
<newline/>
<image name="par"/>
cell of the Assystaunce w
<super id="0103" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 her ma
<super id="0106" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 by vertue of her contracte hathe
<newline/>
ben pleased to yeeld them for theire relefe, Yf they had not ben
<newline/>
placed in the said cautyonarie townes, yet muste they of necessetie
<newline/>
have ben placed in some other townes where they should have receaved
<newline/>
lyke allowaunces in every respect.
<newline/>
<catchword id="0110">
And
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0114">
fol.269v
</folioref>
 And therefore as yt hathe ben heretofore answered, it maie be with reason
<newline/>
maintayned that those other townes w
<super id="0129" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 by this meane have ben freed, and
<newline/>
where they should have otherwyse ben placed should be contributaries unto
<newline/>
the Cawtyonarie townes for the same, And yf they replie, as yt ys
<newline/>
lykelie they will, that yf those Bandes had ben placed in other frontrie
<newline/>
Townes where the Countrie might have reaped benefitt by theire service
<newline/>
they would have ben contented to have borne theire chardge; It maye
<newline/>
be answered that considering the 
<person id="0438" person_id="Parma, A">
Duke of Parma
</person>
 hathe now well neere
<newline/>
a yeere and a halfe ben continewallie in 
<place id="0441" place_id="Flanders">
Flanders
</place>
 w
<super id="0126" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 intente as yt
<newline/>
was thought to have attempted somewhat upon the Islandes or upon
<newline/>
<place id="0445" place_id="Ostend">
Ostende
</place>
 or 
<place id="0449" place_id="Bergen op Zoom">
Berghen
</place>
 as now yt falleth out in 
<image name="par"/>
te true, they could
<newline/>
not have ben more aptlie placed in any other Towne where they mght
<newline/>
so readily ben drawen out to serve uppon any occasion duringe his
<newline/>
continewaunce there then in 
<place id="0453" place_id="Flushing">
Flussinge
</place>
; w
<super id="0142" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 w
<super id="0145" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 answere yf they
<newline/>
shall not rest satysfied, yo
<super id="0433" replace="">
w
</super>
 may then let them understand that an
<newline/>
other cheefe cause whie those extraordinarie bands were first placed ther
<missing id="0149" type="binding">
e
</missing>
<newline/>
grewe upon the 
<person id="0457" person_id="Hohenlo">
Count Hollockes
</person>
 drawinge downe of certaine forces
<newline/>
into the 
<place id="0460" place_id="Walcheren">
Isle of Walkeren
</place>
 w
<super id="0160" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 intent as 
<deletion id="0409">
the
</deletion>
 o
<super id="0412" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 
<person id="0463" person_id="Russell, W">
Governor of Flushinge
</person>
<newline/>
was enformed to have surprysed certaine Townes in the Islande, and
<newline/>
not w
<super id="0163" replace="ith">
th
</super>
out greate and apparaunt suspic
<overline id="0157" replace="io">
o
</overline>
n of somewhat to have ben
<newline/>
attempted upon the Towne of Flushinge yf he had prevailed in the
<newline/>
first plott: w
<super id="0172" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 her ma
<super id="0168" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 had the rather cause to doubt in respect of the
<newline/>
strange carryage of him selfe towardes the 
<person id="0466" person_id="Dudley, R">
Earle of Leicester
</person>
 then Gover
<newline/>
nor of those Countries at the time of his laste beinge in the said Contryes
<newline/>
But now these Jelosies and doubtes beinge removed and taken awaie,
<newline/>
and that her ma
<super id="0180" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 ys sufficientlie 
<image name="par"/>
swaded of theire constancie, good
<newline/>
will and devotyon towardes her; there shall shortlie order be given that
<newline/>
the Garrysons of those Townes shalbe reduced to theire former nombers
<newline/>
agreed upon by the contracte, so as they shall have no juste cause to
<newline/>
complaine further in that behalfe. And for soche other monye for
<newline/>
imprestes or victuaelles w
<super id="0191" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they have furnished or hathe any waie ben
<newline/>
yssued out of theire 
<hand id="0188" type="scribe" Description="">
Magazyns
</hand>
 to the said Garrysons or other her ma
<super id="0195" replace="jesties">
tes
</super>
<newline/>
Subjectes in her paie, the same shalbe defalked out of theire entertainem
<super id="0198" replace="entes">
tes
</super>
<newline/>
and paies to be answered and repaied unto them after an accompt shalbe
<newline/>
passed betweene her ma
<super id="0203" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 and them: But for soche sommes of money
<newline/>
and other chardges as have ben by them dysbursed to certaine extraordy-
<newline/>
nary bands w
<super id="4862" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 were in theire owne paie beinge no 
<image name="par"/>
cell of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e nomb
<super id="0211" replace="er">
r
</super>
<newline/>
contained in the contract, her ma
<super id="0215" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 seeth no reason consideringe the many
<newline/>
<catchword id="0219">
folde
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0223">
fol.270r
</folioref>
 manyfolde chardges she hathe ben otherwyse at for theire defence that they
<newline/>
should seeke to be rembursed thereof at her Highnes handes.
<newline/>
<newline/>
3 And for that they desier that order maie be taken that the Bandes
<newline/>
in her majesties paie maie be kept full and compleate, yo
<super id="0231" replace="">
u
</super>
<newline/>
shall let them understande that for the footebandes (as her Ma
<super id="0235" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
ys enformed by the Commyssaries of Musters) theye have
<newline/>
noe cause to complaine of theire defectes: And for the
<newline/>
horsbandes for that her Highnes cannot convenientlie spare soche
<newline/>
nombers of horse out of this Realme as are requisite to make up
<newline/>
the full nomber agreed uppon by the Contracte; she caused an offer
<newline/>
to be made unto them to supplie certaine bandes of horse whiche
<newline/>
double so many Footemen, whiche as her Majestie conceaveth
<newline/>
cannot but be more beneficiall for theire service consideringe they
<newline/>
stande uppon a defensive warre, But herein her Majestie hathe
<newline/>
not hetherto receaved any direct answer from them in this behalfe
<newline/>
not withstandinge they have ben sollicited bothe by the 
<person id="0469" person_id="Bertie, P">
Lorde
<newline/>
Willoughbie
</person>
 and 
<person id="0472" person_id="Killegrew, H">
Master Killygrewe
</person>
 and also Ortell made
<newline/>
acquainted therewithe so as the lot thereof groweth by theire
<newline/>
defaulte.
<newline/>
<newline/>
4 And where they complaine that they are not made privie
<newline/>
nether to the Musters taken of the saide Bandes neither yet
<newline/>
at the paimentes made by the Threasorer as by the contracte
<newline/>
therein ought to be so as they beinge ignorant of theire owne
<newline/>
estate and what forces they are hable to make cannot provide
<newline/>
soche supplies as were requisite for theire defence, yo
<super id="0454" replace="">
u
</super>
 
<newline/>
aye
<newline/>
tell them that they have ben sondrie times required aswell by m
<super id="0264" replace="aster">
r
</super>
<newline/>
<person id="0475" person_id="Digges, T">
Thomas Digges
</person>
 the late Muster Master, as also by his Brother
<newline/>
<person id="0478" person_id="Digges, J">
James Digges
</person>
 now principall Commyssarie of the Musters
<newline/>
to send theire Commyssaryes to joyne w
<super id="0270" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 them in musteringe
<newline/>
the saide Bandes, but as the saide Digges dothe affirme
<newline/>
the States have failed to sende any at the times appointed
<newline/>
to joyne w
<super id="0279" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 o
<super id="0282" replace="urs">
rs
</super>
: But yf they shall lyke henceforthe to
<newline/>
<catchword id="0287">
appoint
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0291">
fol.270v
</folioref>
 appointe so
<overline id="0294" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
e Commyssaries of theires to joyne wth her
<newline/>
Majesties Mynisters, there shalbe order given unto them to
<newline/>
give notyce to theire Commyssaries of the time when the saide
<newline/>
Musters shalbe taken. And to the ende yt maye be
<newline/>
<newline/>
formed, yow shall put the Lorde Generall in mynde to
<newline/>
direct her Majesties Commyssaries so to doe.
<newline/>
<newline/>
5 Touchinge theire other requestes that the Governo
<super id="0311" replace="">
rs
</super>
 of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Cautyonary
<newline/>
Townes mighte be inhibited to entermeddle henceforthe in
<newline/>
matters of Civill government concerninge the admynistration
<newline/>
of Justice and the ordynarie pollycie in the saide Townes, as
<newline/>
also to forbeare to deale in any matters concerninge theire
<newline/>
Admyralls Jurysdiction, yo
<super id="0451" replace="">
w
</super>
 shall at yo
<super id="0326" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 arryvall at Flusshing
<newline/>
and so lykewyse at 
<place id="0481" place_id="Brill">
the Bryll
</place>
 as yo
<super id="0448" replace="">
w
</super>
 passe up to 
<place id="0484" place_id="Hague">
<image name="thorn"/>
e Hague
</place>
<newline/>
signifie unto the saide Governors that her Majesties
<newline/>
pleasure ys that they forbeare henceforthe to deale any further
<newline/>
in any of those Civill cawses, or causes 
<image name="par"/>
tayninge to Admyrall
<newline/>
Jurysdicc
<overline id="0339" replace="io">
o
</overline>
n otherwyse then as ys agreed uppon in the contract
<newline/>
passed betweene her Majestie and the said Countries, unlesse
<newline/>
yt shalbe in soche causes of controversie as may happen to fall
<newline/>
out betweene so
<overline id="0345" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
e Souldiers of the Garryson and so
<overline id="0348" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
e of
<newline/>
the Burgesses of the saide Townes, at the decydinge whereof to
<newline/>
the ende the matters maye be carryed wth the more indyfferencie
<newline/>
betweene them, It ys thought convenient that the Governor of
<newline/>
the Towne where any controversie shall fall out, or the
<newline/>
Sergeant Major or so
<overline id="0356" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
e other dyscreete to be appointed
<newline/>
by the saide Governo
<super id="0360" replace="">
r
</super>
, should be present at the hearinge and
<newline/>
decydinge of any soche Controversie.
<newline/>
<newline/>
6 And where they desier that the Captaines and Souldiers in her
<newline/>
Majesties paie maye duly paie the excyses and other imposic
<overline id="0367" replace="io">
o
</overline>
ns
<newline/>
aswell as the Souldiers w
<super id="0371" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 serve in theire paie. Yow shall
<newline/>
let them understande that yt ys thought some what harde that
<newline/>
<catchword id="0379">
they
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0383">
fol.271r
</folioref>
 they shoulde insyste in soe presyse a sorte in exactinge soche
<newline/>
imposic
<overline id="0387" replace="io">
o
</overline>
ns of those whoe daily hazard theire lives in theire defence
<newline/>
as to make no dyfference between them and the naturall borne
<newline/>
subjectes of that Countrie; whoe either have theire livinges there, or
<newline/>
are otherwyse releived, havinge sondrie other helpes many other
<newline/>
wayes, Whereas her Ma
<super id="0394" replace="jesties">
tes
</super>
 subjectes beinge meere strangers cann have
<newline/>
no other releefe or helpe then what they have for theire ready monye
<newline/>
and the same at verie highe prices by reason of the Lycences graunted
<newline/>
by them to carry victuaelles to the Ennemy. And therefore yt
<newline/>
ys thought reasonable that they shoulde yeilde unto so
<overline id="0401" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
e favorable
<newline/>
tollerac
<overline id="0405" replace="io">
o
</overline>
n in that behalfe.
<newline/>
<newline/>
<section id="0416" Section="subscription" Place="none">
<hand id="0421" type="Burghley" Description="">
William Burghley
</hand>
<newline/>
<hand id="0424" type="Bodley" Description="?Walsingham?">
Francis Walsyngham
</hand>
<newline/>
<hand id="0427" type="Bodley" Description="?Waad?">
<person id="0431" person_id="Waad">
William Waad
</person>
.
</hand>
</section>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
