<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="0400">
<folioref id="0311">
fol. 264r
</folioref>
 
<section id="0315" Section="endorsement" Place="none">
Belgia. 1588. November 20. M
<super id="0310" replace="">
r
</super>
 Bodlyes first Instructions
</section>
<newline/>
<section id="0008" Section="signmanual" Place="centre">
Elizabeth R
</section>
 
<newline/>
<newline/>
1 Whereas we have thought meet to call home o
<super id="0012" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 servant 
<person id="0340" person_id="Killegrew, H">
Henrie Killigrewe
</person>
<newline/>
both for our owne service and for his owne causes, who presently supplyeth the
<newline/>
place of a Councello
<super id="0018" replace="">
r
</super>
 for us in the 
<person id="0343" person_id="Council of State">
Councell of Estate
</person>
 in the 
<place id="0366" place_id="United Provinces">
united Provinces
</place>
<newline/>
of the 
<place id="0346" place_id="Low Countries">
Lowe Contries
</place>
 agreable to the contract made on our part with 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 
<person id="0349" person_id="States General">
States
<newline/>
Generall
</person>
: wee have therfore made espetiall choise of you to supplie 
<image name="thorn"/>
at place,
<newline/>
with the assistance of our servant 
<person id="0352" person_id="Gilpin">
George Gilpin
</person>
 who is to serve in place
<newline/>
of an Interpreter, for that as wee are enformed they use the Flemish tongue
<newline/>
in the treating and debating of causes amongest them selves.
<newline/>
<newline/>
2 Our pleasure therfore is that at yo
<super id="0033" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 coming thether you shall instruct yo
<super id="0036" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 self
<newline/>
in such matters as have heretofore been c
<overline id="0040" replace="om">
o
</overline>
mitted unto o
<super id="0043" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 said servant Henrie Kil-
<newline/>
legrewe to deale in with the said generall States, and with the Councell of
<newline/>
estate and others of those Contries touching our service, and to knowe from him
<newline/>
to what points he hath not receaved aunsweare from them, to thend you may
<newline/>
the better deale and proceed with the States to procure their speedie aun-
<newline/>
sweare to our satisfaction.
<newline/>
<newline/>
3 And for that wee have c
<overline id="0059" replace="om">
o
</overline>
mitted divers thinges to o
<super id="0056" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 trustie &amp; welbeloved ser-
<newline/>
vant 
<person id="0355" person_id="Norris, J">
S
<super id="0064" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 John Norris
</person>
 his chardge to bee c
<overline id="0067" replace="om">
o
</overline>
municated unto the said States
<newline/>
as may appeare by the Copie of his Instructions: wee thinck yt meet that
<newline/>
such thinges as shall not bee by him finished for lack of time, or for 
<image name="thorn"/>
<abbreviation id="5489" replace="at">
t
</abbreviation>
 he
<newline/>
shall not find the States generall assembled at the time of his repaire thether
<newline/>
or continuance there, that you doe sollicitt the same and send unto us their aun-
<newline/>
sweares in that behalf.
<newline/>
<newline/>
4 And whereas we have heretofore rec
<overline id="0087" replace="om">
o
</overline>
mended unto the said States generall
<newline/>
<person id="0358" person_id="Schenck, M">
Corronell Shinck
</person>
 and divers others (of both whose names and causes ye
<newline/>
shall receave particular information from our Secreatarie) who as wee
<newline/>
are enformed in steed of favo
<super id="0092" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 have receaved from them verie hard measure,
<newline/>
<catchword id="0095">
wherby
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0129">
fol. 264v
</folioref>
 whereby they doe lay open unto the world their owne ingratitude towards us,
<newline/>
to no small touch of our hono
<super id="0104" replace="ur">
r
</super>
, to see us had in a kind of contempt by those that
<newline/>
are so infinitely bound unto us as they are, a matter so publickly knowen, as
<newline/>
it needeth no debating: Our pleasure therfore is that you shall deale most
<newline/>
earnestly with them in moving them to yeald us better contentment hereafter
<newline/>
in this behalf then heretofore they have done, aswell for their owne creditt, w
<super id="0111" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
<newline/>
receaveth no small blemish by this unkind maner of dealing of theirs towards
<newline/>
us, as also for our hono
<super id="0117" replace="">
r
</super>
 who may in no sort endure to suffer such as have
<newline/>
been and are noted to stand well affected towards us, so injuriously handled
<newline/>
as they are, espetially the parties by us recomended, having been men of best
<newline/>
desert, and such of whose service they have most need, namely, Coronell Shinck
<newline/>
being for valour, courage and conduct (accompanied besides with an ex-
<newline/>
traordinarie good fortune) one of the rare men of this our age. And to the
<newline/>
end the reparation that wee require in this behalf may not bee delaied w
<super id="0125" replace="ith">
th
</super>
<newline/>
some aunsweare in generall termes: wee thinck yt convenient that you should
<newline/>
urge them to yeald their particular aunsweare to such requests as have been
<newline/>
heretofore rec
<overline id="0131" replace="om">
o
</overline>
mended by us.
<newline/>
<newline/>
5 Amongest other thinges fytt to be remembred unto them, you shall lett them
<newline/>
understand that wee, hearing that 
<image name="thorn"/>
e States generall doe oft times dissolve,
<newline/>
and that the Counsell of Estate have their authoritie so restreyned as they
<newline/>
cannot upon such extraordinarie events as fall out in these Contries, full
<newline/>
of perill and daunger, and require speedie resolution, yeld that timely re-
<newline/>
medie that were expedient, doe thincke yt most convenient (thenemie being
<newline/>
so strong as he is in the field) that you doe advise them in o
<super id="0147" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 name to conti-
<newline/>
nue their assemblies, or els to enlarge the authoritie of the Councell of Estate.
<newline/>
But before you deale herein wee would have you particularly enforme yo
<super id="0144" replace="ur">
r
</super>
<newline/>
self both by our servant Henrie Killegrewe and others of the Councell of
<newline/>
<catchword id="0151">
Estate
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0155">
fol. 265r
</folioref>
 Estate that you shall learne by him to bee men of best judgement and best
<newline/>
affected to the good of those Contries, what were fitt in particulareties to be
<newline/>
urged in our name in that behalf, to thend you may proceed therein with
<newline/>
the better effect.
<newline/>
<newline/>
6 And whereas we have been given to understand aswell by l
<overline id="0166" replace="etter">
re
</overline>
s from 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 
<person id="0361" person_id="Bertie, P">
L.
<newline/>
Willoughbie
</person>
 unto us, as from our servant Henrie Killegrewe that the
<newline/>
last Instructions given by the States generall to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Counsell of Estate,
<newline/>
conteine sondrie points that are directly repugnant to the contract w
<super id="0175" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
<newline/>
they have made with us, as is plainely sett downe both by 
<person id="0364" person_id="Clerke, Dr">
docto
<super id="0178" replace="">
r
</super>
 Clerke
</person>
<newline/>
and our servaunt 
<person id="0367" person_id="Beale, R">
Robert Beale
</person>
, who have had the viewe and considerac
<overline id="0182" replace="io">
o
</overline>
n
<newline/>
of them: Our pleasure therfore is that you shall deale with the States
<newline/>
most earnestly for the speedie reformation and redresse thereof in such sort
<newline/>
as 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Contract passed between us and them bee not anie way abridged
<newline/>
or infringed by them.
<newline/>
<newline/>
7 And for that wee find that by reason of the licenses graunted by the States
<newline/>
and by other meanes underhand used by the 
<person id="0370" person_id="Philip II">
king of Spaines
</person>
 ministers,
<newline/>
the said king and his Armados have heretofore been furnished from thence
<newline/>
of great stoare both of Cordage, graine, and sondrie other provisions,
<newline/>
without the w
<super id="0334" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 he had never been able to sett forth to the seas so huge an
<newline/>
armie, and so well stoared with all kind of necessaries, which (as since
<newline/>
yt hath been proved) he minded to have employed against this o
<super id="0197" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 Realm,
<newline/>
had not god of his great goodnes broken his ambitious desseigne so as
<newline/>
yf he may nowe bee kept from drawing like provisions out of those Con-
<newline/>
tries and other Contries (for the stay whereof wee have taken some order)
<newline/>
he shall not in manie yeares been able to drawe together so great forces
<newline/>
of that strength as those were the last yeare. You shall therfore deale
<newline/>
most effectually with the said States to inhibite the transportation of
<newline/>
anie like c
<overline id="0198" replace="om">
o
</overline>
modities into 
<place id="0373" place_id="Spain">
Spaine
</place>
, the same to be ordeyned with great
<newline/>
penalties and with severe punishment against the offendors: adding ther-
<newline/>
to that yf anie such provisions shalbe found in anie shipp eyther of those
<newline/>
Contries or of anie other, that shall come within the power of anie of our
<newline/>
owne shippes or into anie of our ports, we will take 
<image name="thorn"/>
e same shippes con-
<newline/>
fiscate, as ayders of our open enemies.
<newline/>
<newline/>
8 Being enformed that neyther the States generall nor 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 
<person id="0376" person_id="Council of War">
Counsell of
<newline/>
warre
</person>
 in those Contries doe acquaint the L. Willoughbye with such 
<newline/>
<catchword id="0214">
resoluc
<overline id="0211" replace="io">
o
</overline>
ns
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0218">
fol.265v
</folioref>
 resolucions as they take in martyall affayres nor with the disposing of
<newline/>
their forces for the withstanding of thenemie wee thinck yt therfore verie
<newline/>
convenient that you should at your arrival there enforme your selfe
<newline/>
thoroughly at the L. Willoughbies hands, howe and in what sort they
<newline/>
doe carie them selves towards him aswell in imparting unto him their
<newline/>
<newline/>
roceeding in martiall causes as also with 
<image name="thorn"/>
e matters of pollecie ten-
<newline/>
ding to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e good government of those Contries: And in case upon confe-
<newline/>
rence with him you shall find that they doe not make him acquainted
<newline/>
with their proceeding in matters of government as well in martiall
<newline/>
causes as otherwise, in such ample sort as was agreed on in 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Contract
<newline/>
that passed between us and those Contries: then our pleasure is that
<newline/>
you shall take some particular notes from him wherein they fayle
<newline/>
to observe 
<image name="thorn"/>
e said contract, to thend you may in our name charge the
<newline/>
said States Generall therewithall, and require of them better obser-
<newline/>
vation thereof in time to come, and that o
<super id="0251" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 Generall the L. Willoughby
<newline/>
bee from time to time made acquainted with their Martiall affayres
<newline/>
and to bee present at 
<image name="thorn"/>
e debating of the same, to thend he may both give
<newline/>
his advice and assent to such thinges as he shall find meet for the
<newline/>
good of those Contries to bee put in execution.
<newline/>
<newline/>
9 And whereas wee have been enformed that 
<image name="thorn"/>
e L. Willoughbie hath both at
<newline/>
<block id="0329" Box="None" Position="Left" Direction="horizontal">
<drawing id="0326">
florilegium
</drawing>
</block>
 
<newline/>
sondrie times past and shall dayly have occasion to disburse good so
<overline id="5482" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
es of
<newline/>
money for the enterteyning of intelligences out of thenemies Contrie to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
end to bee enformed of his proceedings, a matter verie necessarie and be-
<newline/>
hovefull for 
<image name="thorn"/>
e guyding and administring of manie matters of great
<newline/>
importance tending aswell to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e annoyance of the'nemie, as for the a-
<newline/>
voyding of some daungerous attempts against the said Contries, and
<newline/>
for the which 
<image name="thorn"/>
e States Generall did yeald an allowance to our
<newline/>
Late Cousen 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 
<person id="0379" person_id="Dudley, R">
Erle of Leycester
</person>
 in the time of his government, by an
<newline/>
increase of his monethly enterteinement for 
<image name="thorn"/>
<abbreviation id="5490" replace="at">
t
</abbreviation>
 purpose: Our plea-
<newline/>
sure is that you should move 
<image name="thorn"/>
e States to make also some competent
<newline/>
allowance to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e said L. Willoughbie for 
<image name="thorn"/>
e said matter of intelligence,
<newline/>
as in reason they ought, and not to expect that the same should be allowed
<newline/>
by us, considering that it is no way employed to our behoufe but only
<newline/>
for 
<image name="thorn"/>
e service and good of those Contries. And wee thinck yt also
<newline/>
meet that upon some just occasion to be taken by you at your discretion,
<newline/>
you should lett them understand as by way of your owne opinion, but
<newline/>
not so directed by us, that you thinck wee could like well 
<image name="thorn"/>
<abbreviation id="5491" replace="at">
t
</abbreviation>
 they
<newline/>
<catchword id="0277">
should
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0281">
fol. 266r
</folioref>
 should use some gratuitie eyther by yearely allowance or otherwise
<newline/>
to him, towards his great charges which he susteyneth in their ser-
<newline/>
vice, and by way of thankfulnes towards a nobleman, consuming
<newline/>
his patrimonie, hazarding his lyfe, and absenting him self from
<newline/>
his frends and Contrie so long a time for their cause.
<newline/>
<newline/>
10 And whereas some overture hath heretofore been made unto us by 
<person id="0382" person_id="Ortell, J">
M
<super id="0290" replace="aster">
r
</super>
<newline/>
Ortell
</person>
 upon direction receaved from some of the States Generall who
<newline/>
carrie greatest sway among them, that wee would bee pleased for 
<image name="thorn"/>
<abbreviation id="5492" replace="at">
t
</abbreviation>
<newline/>
they nowe find great fault with the weakenes of the bands both
<newline/>
horsemen and footemen serving in our pay, to yeald unto them a
<newline/>
so
<overline id="5485" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
e of money farr inferior to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e charges wee are nowe at, in lieu
<newline/>
of the said assystau
<overline id="0301" replace="nc">
c
</overline>
e: wee can bee content that you shall deale
<newline/>
with such persons as he shall nominate unto you, in such sort as to
<newline/>
you in discretion shalbe thought meet, and to see what 
<image name="thorn"/>
e said offer
<newline/>
wilbe, and howe probably they can make yt appeare unto you,
<newline/>
that they shalbe able with the said so
<overline id="5488" replace="mm">
m
</overline>
e of money to put them selves
<newline/>
in as sufficient strength as having the forces they nowe have from
<newline/>
us by vertue of the contract. And of your proceeding therein
<newline/>
you shall advertise us, to thend we may thereupon give unto you such
<newline/>
further direction as by us shalbe thought meete.
<newline/>
<newline/>
<section id="0314" Section="subscription" Place="none">
Francis Walsyngham
</section>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
