<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="0072">
<folioref id="0002">
fol.369r
</folioref>
 
<section id="0011" Section="lateraddition" Place="top_left">
1592 22 Decem
<abbreviation id="0005" replace="ber">
b
</abbreviation>
 To M
<super id="0008" replace="aster">
r
</super>
 Bodly
</section>
<newline/>
<section id="0015" Section="signmanual" Place="none">
Elizabeth R
</section>
<newline/>
Trustie and welbeloved we greet you well. It is well knowne to you that we have often heretofore both written to 
<person id="0082" person_id="States General">
the States
</person>
 in
<newline/>
favour of 
<person id="0079" person_id="Sonoy">
Collonell Snoy
</person>
, and likewise charged you w
<super id="0020" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 manie commaundem
<super id="0024" replace="ent">
t
<image name="es"/>
</super>
 to accompanie our saide l
<overline id="0027" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s w
<super id="0030" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 yo
<super id="0033" replace="ur">
r
</super>
<newline/>
parsonall sollicitation, w
<super id="0037" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 thoughe we 
kno
we you have done, Yet hath the same ben hitherto w
<super id="0040" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 so litle fruite to
<newline/>
him, as we cannot but be grieved that so earnest a desire, as they may discerne that we have to doe him good,
<newline/>
shoulde be so litle regarded by them. And therefore we have now written unto them rather an expostulation,
<newline/>
then a request, as you may perceive by the copie herew
<super id="0046" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 sent you; w
<super id="0049" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 our pleasure is that you shall by
<newline/>
speache delyver unto them more at large, urging such argument
<image name="es"/>
, as by this and by former instruction concerning
<newline/>
the same, you may conceave our request to be grounded on; And specially this that as we doe take (and so have
<newline/>
plainly signified to them) our honor to be greatly interessed in the successe of this matter: So yf it shalbe otherwise
<newline/>
then to our contentment &amp; then we may justly saie that we have deserved of them, they shall looke for none other
<newline/>
measure at our handes in the like or anie other matter, wherein they shall have occasion to crave our favour, then
<newline/>
such as is fitt to be requited to unthanckfull men. 
<section id="0069" Section="subscription" Place="none">
Gyven under our Signet at our honour of Hampton courte
<newline/>
the xxj
<super id="0060" replace="">
th
</super>
 daye of December 
<underline id="0063">
1592
</underline>
. In the xxxv
<super id="0066" replace="">
th
</super>
 yere of our Reigne.
</section>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
