<transcript>
<page num="1">
<addressleaf id="2332">
<folioref id="1638">
fol.91v
</folioref>
 
<section id="1654" Section="endorsement" Place="none">
<hand id="1651" type="Bodley" Description="">
Copie of a l
<overline id="1648" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
 to yo
<super id="1645" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 2 of Fe
<abbreviation id="1642" replace="bruary">
b
</abbreviation>
 1591.
</hand>
</section>
<newline/>
<section id="1661" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
2 Fe
<abbreviation id="1658" replace="bruary">
b
</abbreviation>
 91/2
</section>
</addressleaf>
<newline/>
<lettertext id="2335">
<folioref id="1281">
fol.89r
</folioref>
 May it please your good L. In the conference desired
<newline/>
by the 
<person id="1384" person_id="Rudolf II">
Emperors
</person>
 
<person id="1388" person_id="Bylant">
Ambassado
<super id="1286" replace="">
r
</super>
,
</person>
 wherof I made mention in 
<newline/>
my laste to yo
<super id="1290" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. I should be over tedious to recite
<newline/>
every point that passed heere between us. But yet as
<newline/>
much as is material I thought good to advertise w
<super id="1295" replace="ith">
th
</super>
<newline/>
the first opportunitie. All his speeches tended to feele
<newline/>
what I would saie to his proposal of a peace, and by
<newline/>
mee to understand, how her 
<person id="1391" person_id="Elizabeth">
Ma
<super id="1309" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
</person>
 and 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 
<person id="1394" person_id="States General">
States
</person>
 were
<newline/>
affected in the matter. But because I would not feed
<newline/>
him w
<super id="1306" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 a frivolous hope, of knowing that by me, w
<super id="1303" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I
<newline/>
knewe not yet my self, I let him plainelie understand,
<newline/>
that, for her Ma
<super id="1316" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 inclination, it was unknowen unto mee,
<newline/>
and likewise of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e States, I could not speake but by
<newline/>
conjecture. But in case hee would acquaint me w
<super id="1320" replace="ith">
th
</super>
<newline/>
the principall drift of his p
<overline id="1328" replace="resent">
nt
</overline>
 Ambassade, and w
<super id="1325" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
qualitie of those conditions, that are intended to bee
<newline/>
offered, I would then as a private 
<image name="par"/>
son, and by waie
<newline/>
of communication tell him franklie my opinion. Upon this
<newline/>
hee protested, that as alwaies hee 
<image name="pro"/>
fessed, and his father
<newline/>
before him the reformed religion, so hee could not but tender
<newline/>
the cause of these countreis: and in that respect would
<newline/>
rather suffer any miserie, then become an instrument for
<newline/>
the Spaniard, whom hee hated from his heart, to ruine
<newline/>
their estate. For w
<super id="1348" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 his purpose was no other, but
<newline/>
to deale, as I requested, verie roundlie and syncerely,
<newline/>
and to disclose the whole dessigne of this p
<overline id="1353" replace="resent">
nt
</overline>
 legation.
<newline/>
Howbeit hee requested mee to take it of him, as privately
<newline/>
spoken, w
<super id="1358" replace="ith">
th
</super>
out any commission: upon confidence onely
<newline/>
that I would deale againe as roundlie in retourning my 
<newline/>
opinion. First for himself, his p
<overline id="1368" replace="resent">
nt
</overline>
 charge was no
<newline/>
other, but to negotiate w
<super id="1365" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e States, that 
<image name="thorn"/>
e rest of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e
<newline/>
Ambassado
<super id="1375" replace="">
rs
</super>
 mighte have licence to come hether: or if they
<newline/>
mighte not be permitted to come unto the Hage, that some
<newline/>
<folioref id="1379">
fol.89v
</folioref>
 place should be assigned upon the frontiers, or at least
<newline/>
that they would send their Deputies to 
<place id="1398" place_id="Collen">
Collen.
</place>
 For the
<newline/>
rest of the Ambassado
<super id="1386" replace="">
rs
</super>
, their commission was no other, but
<newline/>
to induce the States to a Treatie: and 
<image name="thorn"/>
<abbreviation id="1668" replace="at">
t
</abbreviation>
 a Treaty being 
<newline/>
admitted, they were to send againe unto the Emperour
<newline/>
for some furder instruction; not having yet receaved, any
<newline/>
articles, or matter to propose unto 
<image name="thorn"/>
e States. But yet hee
<newline/>
thought, that in the end, the motions to be made would
<newline/>
come to this effect; That seing there was no hope to 
<newline/>
reconcile this people to 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 
<person id="1401" person_id="Philip II">
K. of 
<highlight id="1397" Type="italic">
Spaine,
</highlight>
</person>
 whome by waie of
<newline/>
abjuration they had excluded for ever from the rule of these
<newline/>
countreis, they should therfore condescend, to unite them
<newline/>
selves in one w
<super id="1381" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e rest of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e 17 Provinces, and al in 
<newline/>
general to acknowledge the Empero
<super id="1406" replace="">
r
</super>
 for their Souverain
<newline/>
and after his decease the heires of his bodie, or for faulte
<newline/>
of such heires, to make choise in his famelie, of whomsoever
<newline/>
they moste desired. Hee delivered this but as a plott,
<newline/>
not accorded as yet w
<super id="1414" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e K. of 
<highlight id="1417" Type="italic">
Spaine,
</highlight>
 but projected by
<newline/>
great personages, who, if the Treatie bee accepted, make
<newline/>
it easie enough to compas either by procuring a mariage
<newline/>
between 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Empero
<super id="1427" replace="">
r
</super>
 and the 
<person id="1404" person_id="Isabella">
daughter
</person>
 of 
<highlight id="1424" Type="italic">
Spaine,
</highlight>
 and the
<newline/>
inheritance of these countreis to bee given in dowry: or by
<newline/>
some other such persuasion, as, hee was well assured, would
<newline/>
take good effect. So that if the righte of Spaine were
<newline/>
derived to the Empero
<super id="1434" replace="">
r
</super>
, and such other conditions admitted
<newline/>
w
<super id="1438" replace="ith">
th
</super>
all, as the States mighte indent for their furder securitie,
<newline/>
there was no occasion to his understanding, why that either
<newline/>
the people of these Provinces, or any of their allies, should
<newline/>
stand in any doute of the puissance of 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Spaniard.
<newline/>
<newline/>
As touching 
<image name="thorn"/>
e premisses I made him this answear, that
<newline/>
first for his owne sute I sawe no likelihoode of leave,
<newline/>
for the rest of the Commissioners to come unto the 
<highlight id="1450" Type="italic">
Hage
</highlight>
<newline/>
<folioref id="1454">
fol.90r
</folioref>
 or to any place upon the confines. They were many
<newline/>
in nomber, and some of them, they knewe by former expe-
<newline/>
rience, to bee verie ill affected to the cause of these
<newline/>
countreis, and not any but himself well instructed in
<newline/>
religion. By reason wherof wee should alwaies bee in
<newline/>
feare of their couvert proceeding, and corrupting of the
<newline/>
people. Moreover there were many respect
<image name="es"/>
, for w
<super id="1464" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
<newline/>
I thought they would refuse to send any man to 
<highlight id="1468" Type="italic">
Collen
</highlight>
.
<newline/>
For the Brute alone of their sending mighte cause an
<newline/>
alteration among the commons of this Countrey; and
<newline/>
might turne to their prejudice both in 
<place id="1408" place_id="England">
England,
</place>
 and
<newline/>
in 
<place id="1411" place_id="France">
Fraunce:
</place>
 where the occasion of their sending would
<newline/>
bee knowen to a fewe, but moste men would imagine, that
<newline/>
they had yeelded alredy to an actual Treaty w
<super id="1478" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 
<image name="thorn"/>
e Ennemy.
<newline/>
And if their errand were no other, but to worke this
<newline/>
people to a Treatie, it mighte aswell bee 
<image name="par"/>
fourmed by one
<newline/>
as by many, and as soone by their letters as by their
<newline/>
presence. For they should not need to dout, but that
<newline/>
this countrey would bee forward, if her Ma
<super id="1487" replace="jestie">
tie
</super>
 w
<super id="1490" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 whom
<newline/>
they had contracted, and the 
<person id="1415" person_id="Navarre">
french King
</person>
, who was
<newline/>
greatlie interessed would assent therunto. And for my
<newline/>
self I was persuaded, that if the Empero
<super id="1497" replace="">
r
</super>
 would
<newline/>
endevour by vertue of his imperial autoritie among
<newline/>
christian Princes, to cause by the Pope, and King of 
<highlight id="1501" Type="italic">
Spaine
</highlight>
<newline/>
to w
<super id="1505" replace="ith">
th
</super>
draw their forces out of France, both the Queene
<newline/>
and the king would p
<overline id="1509" replace="resent">
nt
</overline>
lie and willinglie hearken to
<newline/>
any treatie that might stand w
<super id="1513" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 their safetie. And
<newline/>
until such time as that bee don, it was in vaine, to 
<newline/>
my thinking, to make any motion to them, or to this people:
<newline/>
Astouching that project of reducing these Provinces to
<newline/>
the Empero
<super id="1522" replace="">
rs
</super>
 obedience, being don in that order as hee
<newline/>
had declared by resignation of the King, and suche
<newline/>
covenants accorded as were meet to bee required, as far
<newline/>
<folioref id="1526">
fol.90v
</folioref>
 as I could conceave in a matter of that moment, and so
<newline/>
newly proposed, it would not be rejected. But yet I
<newline/>
thought it would prove a tedious peece of worke. For 
<newline/>
to send first into England and France to persuade their
<newline/>
Ma
<super id="1537" replace="jesties">
ties
</super>
 to embrace a pacification, and then to use int
<super id="1534" replace="er">
r
</super>
cession
<newline/>
w
<super id="1547" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 the 
<person id="1419" person_id="Clement">
Pope,
</person>
 and w
<super id="1544" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 
<highlight id="1541" Type="italic">
Spaine
</highlight>
 to revoke their forces; and
<newline/>
after to capitulate upon the points of making over the
<newline/>
inheritance of the Countrey, it would require such lengthe
<newline/>
of time, as I see litell cause to expect a good issew.
<newline/>
Againe considering how the King shalbee touched in honor
<newline/>
in the end of so many yeares warres, and after the
<newline/>
consumtion of so great a treasure, to bee forced by a handful
<newline/>
of people, and by his owne vassels, to surrender his title
<newline/>
in so many Provinces, it is to bee presumed, that hee
<newline/>
will use as many shiftes to protract the time, as every lighte
<newline/>
occasion shall minister unto him: that if he happen to
<newline/>
prevaile in some battel in France, hee will p
<overline id="1561" replace="resent">
nt
</overline>
ly retract
<newline/>
all these offers of the Empero
<super id="1566" replace="">
r
</super>
. To reherse what hee
<newline/>
replied unto every part of my speeche, were to comber your
<newline/>
L. w
<super id="1575" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 unnecessarie matter. In the end he concluded,
<newline/>
that hee thought, as I had said, there was nothing to bee
<newline/>
hoped in dealing w
<super id="1572" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 the States, unles England and France
<newline/>
were first sollicited, and cessation of armes procured in
<newline/>
France. That had also bin alwaies the opinion of the
<newline/>
Emperor, who, he knew, was desirous to have made his motion
<newline/>
there at first, but that no intercession was used unto him,
<newline/>
and of himself hee had no cause. For in the sending of 
<newline/>
his commissioners to deale w
<super id="1584" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 these Provinces, he was
<newline/>
moved unto it by the Princes of 
<place id="1422" place_id="Germany">
<highlight id="1589" Type="italic">
Germanie,
</highlight>
</place>
 being also bound
<newline/>
therunto, in as muche as these contreis depend from the
<newline/>
Empire; and were alwaies concluded in the circle of
<newline/>
<place id="1426" place_id="Burgundy">
<highlight id="1595" Type="italic">
Burgundie.
</highlight>
</place>
 But if the States would be 
<image name="par"/>
suaded to
<newline/>
<folioref id="1599">
fol.91r
</folioref>
 write unto the Empero
<super id="1605" replace="">
r
</super>
, and certifie expreslie that w
<super id="1602" replace="ith">
th
</super>
out
<newline/>
the notice and assent of England and France, they
<newline/>
wil not harken to any motion: hee did not make any
<newline/>
dout, but that the Empero
<super id="1611" replace="">
r
</super>
 therupon would fraime his
<newline/>
course to their content. This is the somme of a 
<newline/>
longer conference, of w
<super id="1618" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I humbly beseech you to
<newline/>
consyder, what is fitt to be im
<image name="par"/>
ted to her Ma
<super id="1621" replace="jestye">
tye
</super>
, and
<newline/>
if any im
<image name="par"/>
fection bee noted in my dealing, to excuse it
<newline/>
w
<super id="1627" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 a worde of your honorable favour. 
<section id="1664" Section="subscription" Place="none">
and so I take
<newline/>
my humble leave. 
<highlight id="1634" Type="italic">
Hage. Feb
<abbreviation id="1631" replace="ruary">
r
</abbreviation>
 2 1591
</highlight>
</section>
</lettertext>
<newline/>
</page>
</transcript>
