<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="0128">
<folioref id="0002">
fol.283r
</folioref>
 
<section id="0011" Section="lateraddition" Place="top_left">
1592 27 Au
<abbreviation id="0005" replace="gust">
g.
</abbreviation>
 To M
<super id="0008" replace="aster">
r
</super>
 Bodly.
</section>
<newline/>
By the Queene:
<newline/>
<section id="0016" Section="signmanual" Place="none">
Elizabeth R
</section>
<newline/>
Trusty and welbelovid we greet you well. Since o
<super id="0020" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 last l
<overline id="0023" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s unto you for the speedie
<newline/>
sending awaie of the sixtene Bandes of footemen into 
<place id="0121" place_id="France">
Fraunce
</place>
, which w
<super id="0027" replace="ith">
th
</super>
 other nombers shall
<newline/>
make 4000 footemen in 
<place id="0133" place_id="Brittany">
Bretaigne
</place>
 we have thought it verie necessarie to have to serve
<newline/>
with so manie footemen, one bande of an hundred horsemen, to be sent also thether for the
<newline/>
necessarie service and succour of our said footemen And therfore have determined, that either S
<super id="0033" replace="ir">
r
</super>
<newline/>
<person id="0126" person_id="Poley, J">
John Pooley
</person>
, or 
<person id="0130" person_id="Parker, N">
S
<super id="0037" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Nicholas Parker
</person>
, wherof either of them have in charge and paie,
<newline/>
one hundred horsemen, shall with one of their band
<image name="es"/>
 or with so manie, as shall make a bande
<newline/>
of one hundred, passe over into Fraunce with the said footemen, or assone after as they can.
<newline/>
And because we are not certaine howe theis two have their bandes furnished, to be readie for
<newline/>
this service: (although we thinke neither of them can alledge anie reasonable cause of their
<newline/>
want): We will and c
<overline id="0051" replace="om">
o
</overline>
maunde you, to send for them bothe, speedelie unto you, and imparte
<newline/>
this our determinac
<overline id="0048" replace="io">
o
</overline>
n unto them, and charge them in o
<super id="0063" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 name, that one of them do prepare
<newline/>
their bande, being in charge of one hundred, saving the allowaunce of their dead paie, to passe
<newline/>
over into France, as our footemen are appointed, with the said nombre of one hundred horsmen.
<newline/>
And if it shold so fall out (w
<super id="0060" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 we shold have cause gretlie to mislike) that neither of them
<newline/>
alone, can be able to furnish the said full nomber: then rather, then the service shold not
<newline/>
be performed, we will you in our name, to c
<overline id="0071" replace="om">
o
</overline>
maund anie one of them two, to passe over w
<super id="0068" replace="ith">
th
</super>
<newline/>
suche nomber, as anie of them have, and can carrie out of that Cuntrie, and that the other of
<newline/>
the said two Captaines, that shall not 
tak
e this Journey, shall deliver to him that shall goe,
<newline/>
in the same, so manie of his bande, as shalbe sufficientlie furnished with horse and Armo
<super id="0077" replace="">
r
</super>
<newline/>
to make up, the full nomber of an hundred horse, saving the dead paies, to serve with him as
<newline/>
you shall up
<overline id="0085" replace="po">
o
</overline>
n good considerac
<overline id="0082" replace="io">
o
</overline>
n finde the metest man to be comaunded in our name. And
<newline/>
this our determinacion you shall deliver to them booth by speeche in o
<super id="0089" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 name, and also by shewing
<newline/>
to them this our comaundement in writing, and if anie of them bothe shall refuse, or delaie
<newline/>
the execuc
<overline id="0094" replace="io">
o
</overline>
n of this service, you shall declare unto them, that the partie refusing, shalbe for
<newline/>
ever shutt out of o
<super id="0098" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 wages, and incurre our further displeasure, according to the quallitie of
<newline/>
their offence. And for the nominacion and election, of the partie of theis two, whom you shall
<newline/>
thinke mete to take the charge upon him, you maie use the advise of 
<person id="0136" person_id="Vere, F">
S
<super id="0103" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Frauncis Veere
</person>
<newline/>
yf convenientlie without delaie of time, you maie receyve his opinion therup
<overline id="0107" replace="po">
o
</overline>
n. 
<hand id="0122" type="scribe" Description="">
And theise
<newline/>
our l
<overline id="0111" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s shalbe your sufficiente warrante in this behalf. 
<section id="0125" Section="subscription" Place="none">
Gyven under our
<newline/>
Signet at Ramsbury the xxvij
<super id="0115" replace="">
th
</super>
 day of August 1592. In the xxxiiij
<super id="0118" replace="">
th
</super>
<newline/>
yere of our raigne.
</section>
</hand>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
