<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="1439">
<folioref id="0775">
fol.210r
</folioref>
 
<section id="0787" Section="lateraddition" Place="none">
<missing id="0781" type="fire">
[Bel]
</missing>
gia 
<missing id="0784" type="fire">
[15]
</missing>
92 Jun 1
<super id="0778" replace="">
0
</super>
</section>
<newline/>
May it please yo
<super id="0797" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 good L. The 24 day of 
<insertion id="0791">
May
</insertion>
 w
<super id="0794" replace="ith">
t
</super>
in a daies
<newline/>
jorney of 
<place id="2217" place_id="Steenwijk">
Steenwicke
</place>
 I receaved her 
<person id="2220" person_id="Elizabeth">
M
<super id="0801" replace="ajesties">
ties
</super>
</person>
 l
<overline id="0804" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s to the 
<person id="2223" person_id="States General">
general
<newline/>
States
</person>
 and to my selfe, w
<super id="0808" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 one from yo
<super id="0811" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. w
<super id="0814" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 were dated the
<newline/>
8 and the 9 of the same. Advertised thereby of the pleasure 
<newline/>
of her Hig
<super id="0819" replace="hnes">
nes
</super>
 that I should deale w
<super id="0822" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the 
<person id="2226" person_id="Council of State">
Councel
</person>
 and 
<person id="2229" person_id="Maurice">
Count
<newline/>
Maurice
</person>
, as well as w
<super id="0826" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the States, for sending further succors
<newline/>
to the service of the 
<person id="2232" person_id="Navarre">
Kinge,
</person>
 I parted presently upon it, and
<newline/>
came the same day where the Count was encamped. Having
<newline/>
signified there unto him her M
<super id="0832" replace="ajesties">
ties
</super>
 desire, and used requisit
<newline/>
persuasion, to move him to advance it, he made me this
<newline/>
answear, that he was very well assured of the States reso-
<newline/>
lution, not to send for this present any more into 
<place id="2235" place_id="France">
France:
</place>
<newline/>
for that the Contrey had assented to a large contribution
<newline/>
for the atcheiving heere of those attemptes, w
<super id="0840" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 are determine
<missing id="0846" type="erosion">
d
</missing>
<newline/>
this sommer: w
<super id="0850" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 also tende to the assuring of the Province
<newline/>
of 
<place id="2238" place_id="Friesland">
Frise,
</place>
 and that their honor was engaged in the enter
<newline/>
prise of Steenwicke. Whereupon for himselfe, as it was
<newline/>
not a matter, that belonged unto him, but to the states of
<newline/>
the Countrey, so he thought it very hard to be pressed
<newline/>
thereunto, not willing 
<insertion id="0859">
to
</insertion>
 intermeddle ether one way or other
<newline/>
And as touching the troupes, w
<super id="0862" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 her M
<super id="0865" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 required of her
<newline/>
owne intertenment, he was fully persuaded, that assoone
<newline/>
as they were gone, the States would revoke their forces
<newline/>
out of France: and that besides it would occasion a great
<newline/>
discontentment among the people of the
<deletion id="0872">
e
</deletion>
se Provinces,
<newline/>
and cause that nothing would be done ether heere or in
<newline/>
France: w
<super id="0881" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 would prejudice exceedingly both her M
<super id="0878" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 and
<newline/>
them. This was the substance of his answear unto me.
<newline/>
Whereunto I replied, that howsoever the States had already
<newline/>
resolved to imploye their forces heere at home, both her
<newline/>
<folioref id="0887">
fol.210v
</folioref>
 M
<super id="0890" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 and they had but onely one designe, w
<super id="0893" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 was to ruine
<newline/>
the Enemie by all the meanes they coulde devise. And
<newline/>
seing in all apparance, he was already reduced to suche 
<newline/>
termes of extremitie, as an opportunitie nowe served,
<newline/>
to precipitat all his power, and that very shortly by
<newline/>
assisting the Kinge w
<super id="0903" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 suche strength as they were able,
<newline/>
they could not answear in reason to their friendes and
<newline/>
allies, for their wilfull neglect of a notable advantage.
<newline/>
And to that w
<super id="0909" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 he objected that they had levied a subsidie
<newline/>
in regard of their owne estate, and were nowe in suche
<newline/>
an action, as they could not well give over, w
<super id="0915" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the credit
<newline/>
of the contrey, or the peoples satisfaction, it importing
<newline/>
the deliverance of a principall Province, from subjection
<newline/>
of the Enemie, her M
<super id="0922" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 in her l
<overline id="0925" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
 had made sufficient
<newline/>
answear, That if the Enemie in France prevaile of his
<newline/>
dessigne, his losses heere at home of a fewe litle townes
<newline/>
will be soone recovered. And for contenting of the people,
<newline/>
w
<super id="0931" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 can not happely conceave, howe the expending of their mony,
<newline/>
to support a forraine Prince, can redounde unto the contr[ey]
<newline/>
much more beneficiall, then it may doe heere among them[selves]
<newline/>
in these intended exploites, w
<super id="0937" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 are done before their en[.]
<newline/>
and are understoode of them all, and carie a kinde of ce[r]
<newline/>
taintie of that successe that they desire, That I signifi[ed]
<newline/>
was a point, in w
<super id="0952" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 his owne good endevo
<super id="0957" replace="">
r
</super>
, w
<super id="0943" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the rest of [the]
<newline/>
Gouverno
<super id="0960" replace="">
rs
</super>
, and those that have the maneging of the affa[ires]
<newline/>
of their state, was specially required. For if they w[ill]
<newline/>
resolve to concurre in some good forme of a publicke Re[mon]
<newline/>
strance, and travel in suche sorte, as they were able, [with]
<newline/>
the people, it would undoubtedly prove easie, to compa[sse]
<newline/>
their good liking. But howsoever they were inclined
<newline/>
<folioref id="0969">
fol.211r
</folioref>
 for w
<super id="0975" replace="ith">
t
</super>
holding of their owne forces, her M
<super id="0972" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 did expect, that
<newline/>
they would not refuse her, for the enseignes demanded of
<newline/>
the Englishe assistance. For they might drawe out of 
<place id="2241" place_id="Holland">
Holland
</place>
<newline/>
for a present supplie, as good as 15 companies of their owne
<newline/>
pay, w
<super id="0982" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 were reserved heere behinde, for defense against
<newline/>
the Enemie, while the armie is at Steenwicke. They have
<newline/>
also lately intertened, as I writte unto yo
<super id="0987" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. the 17 of the
<newline/>
last, 2000 men of 
<place id="2244" place_id="Juliers">
Juliers,
</place>
 to be imploied in their service
<newline/>
upon certaine weekes warning: so as nothing can impeache
<newline/>
but that to intention of her M
<super id="0993" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 for the use of those that
<newline/>
she requireth, should be willingly accorded. There was
<newline/>
nothing saide to this that was greatly material, nor to
<newline/>
divers other pointes, that I proposed to like effect. But
<newline/>
he concluded all his answear, that for his owne particular
<newline/>
he would nether make nor marre the mater, but leave
<newline/>
it to the States. To the selfe same purpose, as I had dealt
<newline/>
w
<super id="1004" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the Count, I dealt the next day after w
<super id="1007" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the Councel of
<newline/>
estate: who thought the motion out of season, their campe
<newline/>
being settled in the siedge of Steenwicke: the taking
<newline/>
whereof would free the land of Frise of a great contri
<newline/>
bution, amounting yerly at the lest to 24000
<super id="1019" replace="">
<linethrough id="1016" replace="">
l
</linethrough>
</super>
 sterling,
<newline/>
w
<super id="4430" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 is payed to the Enemie by the frontier inhabitants: for
<newline/>
w
<super id="4433" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they thought it impossible to gette the states to yeld unto
<newline/>
it. They urged therew
<super id="1026" replace="ith">
t
</super>
all that the affaires of the King,
<newline/>
did alter very muche, and were now in an other state,
<newline/>
then at the time of the date of her M
<super id="1031" replace="ajesties">
ties
</super>
 l
<overline id="1034" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
. For they had
<newline/>
letters from sondrie places, that 
<person id="2247" person_id="Parma">
Parma
</person>
 was returned,
<newline/>
and in all probabilitie, would give some onsette at his
<newline/>
comming. And where her Hig
<super id="1039" replace="hnes">
nes
</super>
 did require 2000 of her
<newline/>
owne subjects, to be shipped out of hand, they stoode upon
<newline/>
<folioref id="1044">
fol.211v
</folioref>
 the Contract, that they could not in equitie be otherwise
<newline/>
disposed then the contrey shall appoint: for that her M
<missing id="1051" type="fire">
<super id="1048" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
</missing>
<newline/>
hath cautions for the answearing of her charges. In con
<newline/>
clusion they tooke it for a matter appertening to the states
<newline/>
and so remitted me to them. As I had formerly replied
<newline/>
to the Countes allegations, I delivered the same to the Counc[el]
<newline/>
againe, to witte in suche pointes as their speeches agreed:
<newline/>
and declared besides to their further objections, that they
<newline/>
knewe well enough they were able for a time, to spare
<newline/>
a good power to the assisting of the King and yet retaine
<newline/>
sufficient strength, for defense of all their places. And as
<newline/>
for that w
<super id="1065" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they had pleaded upon the mater of rembour-
<newline/>
sement, it was not greatly pertinent. For in a manifest
<newline/>
case, of suche advantage to the cause, they should deale
<newline/>
very strictly w
<super id="1073" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 her M
<super id="1070" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
, if having suffered those of
<newline/>
Holland to send certaine Regiments into France, w
<super id="1077" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out
<newline/>
asking the advise of the rest of the Provinces, they would
<newline/>
ticke at her demand, w
<super id="1082" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 is so orderly imparted and desired
<newline/>
at their handes. Againe, albeit they were unwilling
<newline/>
to take any order in this mater, but put me over to the
<newline/>
states, they were not ignorant notw
<super id="1088" replace="ith">
t
</super>
standing, that th[e]
<newline/>
states intermedling in a cause of this qualitie, was a 
<newline/>
flatte usurpation, and that all the actions of these wa[rres]
<newline/>
by graunt of the Contract were belonging onely to h[er]
<newline/>
M
<super id="1098" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 and to the Colledge of the Councell, wherby her Hig[
<super id="1095" replace="">
nes
</super>
]
<newline/>
had authoritie, as much as all the councel, to appoint [the]
<newline/>
imploiment of their forces for the service of the Con[trey]
<newline/>
I wished them at last, that although they would not [send]
<newline/>
any more of their owne, they should not stand w
<super id="1107" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 her [Majestie]
<newline/>
for the 14 Englishe bandes, w
<super id="1110" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 if they would not per[mitte]
<newline/>
<folioref id="1116">
fol.212r
</folioref>
 to be presently sent, being most of them there and engaged in
<newline/>
the siedge, yet because it was hoped, that in 10 dayes after the 
<newline/>
service would be ended, and because they had besides them suf-
<newline/>
ficient forces of the contrey, to performe the rest that they
<newline/>
intended for the attemptes of this sommer, they should not
<newline/>
make any further question, when Stenwicke was reduced.
<newline/>
To which effect I did desire, that they would fall in consul-
<newline/>
tation, and give the States their best advise. But to that
<newline/>
they would not answear. I had this conference w
<super id="1130" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the
<newline/>
Councel the 25 of May, in the Campe before Steenwicke.
<newline/>
But because they left me to the States, to whome her M
<super id="1135" replace="ajesties">
ties
</super>
<newline/>
l
<overline id="1140" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
 was addressed expressely, and were residing at the Hage,
<newline/>
I came hither thereupon w
<super id="1143" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 all possible speede: where I
<newline/>
found their assembly dissolved for a time, and divers of the
<newline/>
Deputies departed home into their Provinces, so as those
<newline/>
that were remaining, made some doubt of breaking open
<newline/>
her M
<super id="1154" replace="ajesties">
ties
</super>
 l
<overline id="1151" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
, for want of their being in competent number.
<newline/>
But when I had declared to some in particular, that this
<newline/>
recesse of the States, at suche a time as the Contrey had
<newline/>
greatest neede of their service, would seeme a practise for
<newline/>
the nones, to defeate her Highnes of her purpose, and that
<newline/>
I thought shee would goe forward w
<super id="1162" replace="ith">
t
</super>
out attending their
<newline/>
meeting, they assembled then as many as were abiding heere
<newline/>
in place, and used divers communications and commings
<newline/>
toe and froe, to debate the mater w
<super id="1171" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 me: w
<super id="1168" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 was all to one
<newline/>
effect, w
<super id="1175" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the speeches of the Count, and Councell of estate.
<newline/>
But this they added more, that for their Levies in Juliers,
<newline/>
they were for that provision, w
<super id="1185" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they made for Britaine,
<newline/>
and not to be imploied in any other part: for w
<super id="1182" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 also their
<newline/>
shippes, w
<super id="1189" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they promised for their portion are all in a readines
<newline/>
<folioref id="1193">
fol.212v
</folioref>
 so as nowe they doe attend what her Hig
<super id="1197" replace="hnes">
nes
</super>
 will resolve.
<newline/>
Moreover for the companies in Holland, w
<super id="1202" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I alleaged the[y]
<newline/>
might use in lieu of the Englishe, they had freshe intellige[nce]
<newline/>
out of 
<place id="2251" place_id="Brabant">
Brabant,
</place>
 that 
<person id="2257" person_id="Mondragon">
Mondragon
</person>
 was in feeld w
<super id="1205" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 1500
<newline/>
footemen, and towardes 400 horse, and had taken 
<place id="2260" place_id="'s-Gravenwezel">
Sgravenwes[el]
</place>
<newline/>
w
<super id="1211" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 was a place of good strength, appertening to these contrei[s]
<newline/>
From thence, ass it seemeth, he marcheth towardes
<newline/>
<place id="2266" place_id="Turnhout">
Tournhoult
</place>
 and 
<place id="2269" place_id="Westerlo">
Westelo,
</place>
 w
<super id="1218" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 are also castels in our possessio[n]
<newline/>
and as his forces shall augment, as by report they doe daily
<newline/>
they feare some greater mater. For prevention whereof
<newline/>
they might not suffer those troupes to be sent out of
<newline/>
Holland. Lastely they told me, that they had newly
<newline/>
given leave to their Coronels in France, who they though[t]
<newline/>
at this present had scarce in all a 1000 men, to raise their
<newline/>
numbers to 2400: w
<super id="1226" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they were in good hope would satisfie
<newline/>
the Kinge, considering their estate: as they doubted not
<newline/>
also, but her M
<super id="1231" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 would be moved, not to presse them
<newline/>
any more, upon notice of as much, as they had declared,
<newline/>
w
<super id="1236" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they praied me to certifie. For as yet they were
<newline/>
uncertaine, whether in a matter of that consequence
<newline/>
being fewer then they should be, and therefore not aut[ho]
<newline/>
rised to assembled as a colledge, they might answear h[er]
<newline/>
M
<super id="1242" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 by way of a letter: w
<super id="1245" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 yet they meant to put againe [in]
<newline/>
further deliberation. I am borne in hand by 
<person id="2272" person_id="Buzenval">
M
<super id="1251" replace="aster">
r
</super>
 Buz[enval]
</person>
<newline/>
that he hath dealt very earnestly, to helpe this matt[er]
<newline/>
forward, being so commanded by the 
<person id="2275" person_id="Navarre">
Kinge:
</person>
 but hath
<newline/>
no other answear, then that w
<super id="1267" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 I have signified. To [give]
<newline/>
yo
<super id="1261" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. some notice of my privat persuasion, If her M[
<super id="1256" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
]
<newline/>
at first, as she requested them to yeeld some great[er]
<newline/>
aide unto the King, had required there
<super id="1264" replace="ith">
t
</super>
wall in absolu[te]
<newline/>
<folioref id="1271">
fol.213r
</folioref>
 manner, that the 14 Englishe bandes should be presently
<newline/>
embarked, I thinke they had not made any great opposition,
<newline/>
and I am sure it had impeached the composing of their Campe,
<newline/>
whereby there had bin hope, that in the end they would
<newline/>
have spared some enseignes of their owne. Moreover I
<newline/>
hold it my duty to certifie yo
<super id="1282" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. that where her M
<super id="1279" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 doeth
<newline/>
account that the 24 foote companies should make 2000 men
<newline/>
they will not reache to that number in common conjecture
<newline/>
by seven or eight hundred at the lest. For there ar almost
<newline/>
300 comprehended in the allowance of the deade paies,
<newline/>
and of suche persons in every company as never come to
<newline/>
service. It is also supposed that their other defectes, for
<newline/>
want of renforcement out of 
<place id="2278" place_id="England">
England,
</place>
 and by divers other
<newline/>
accidents, and their losses in this siedge, together w
<super id="1293" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 the
<newline/>
numbers that will runne from their captaines, before they
<newline/>
come to be embarked, will stretche in all likelihood, to twice
<newline/>
as many more. For there were slaine and hurt, before I
<newline/>
parted from the campe, not so fewe as a 100 Englishe: of w
<super id="1300" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
<newline/>
there were 60 in one day sent to 
<place id="2281" place_id="Kampen">
Campen,
</place>
 
<place id="2284" place_id="Hoorn">
Horne,
</place>
 
<place id="2287" place_id="Enkhuizen">
Enchusen,
</place>
<newline/>
and 
<place id="2290" place_id="Amsterdam">
Amsterdame
</place>
. And no doubt they have decreased conti-
<newline/>
nually since, and will doe more and more, as they come
<newline/>
to harder service in assalting or otherwise. Upon this
<newline/>
weaknes of the Companies both the states and the Councell
<newline/>
did earnestly insist that being drawen away from hence
<newline/>
they should be forced out of hand to dissolve their armie, the
<newline/>
King should receave but a small relief of men, and at last
<newline/>
by that meanes nothing would be done of the one side or the
<newline/>
other. Because I doe presume, that 
<person id="2293" person_id="Vere, F">
S
<super id="1317" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Francis Vere
</person>
, 
<insertion id="1323">
and
</insertion>
 
<person id="2296" person_id="Sidney, R">
S
<super id="1320" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Robert
<newline/>
Sidney 
</person>
will advertise yo
<super id="1331" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. of all that hath passed, since
<newline/>
their first sitting downe; I should but overtrouble you w
<super id="1328" replace="ith">
t
</super>
<newline/>
<folioref id="1335">
fol.213v
</folioref>
 my particular relation. There is very good hope, that we
<newline/>
shall carie away the place: and wee looke to understand
<newline/>
it w
<super id="1341" replace="ith">
t
</super>
in foure or five dayes. At my being there the towne
<newline/>
was blocked one every side, aproches made unto the counter
<newline/>
scarffe and the most of their gabions placed already. And by
<newline/>
ths time I suppose, they have planted their artillery: of w
<super id="1346" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
<newline/>
there were 47 great peeces, and 11 for the feelde: wherew
<super id="1350" replace="ith">
t
</super>
<newline/>
they purpose to batter in 4 several places, for the making
<newline/>
of two breaches. They have also made a cavallier, upon
<newline/>
w
<super id="1362" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 they appoint to place some peeces of ordinance, for skouring
<newline/>
the ramparts. Besides they have sette certaine pioners a
<newline/>
worke to sappe the walles, and divers ingeno
<super id="1367" replace="">
rs
</super>
, to devise
<newline/>
artificiall fiers, and are determined to put all in execut[ion]
<newline/>
in one day, for the more astonishment of the Enemy.
<newline/>
The towne is very little, and w
<super id="1373" replace="hat">
at
</super>
 garrison is in it, we can
<newline/>
not conjecture. For they have carried themselves very
<newline/>
souldiourlike, and having made many sallies, never left
<newline/>
us a prisoner by whome we might learne the state of th[e]
<newline/>
towne. S
<super id="1380" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Francis Vere hath bin shotte w
<super id="1383" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 a harquebuze in t[he]
<newline/>
small of his left legge, and his brother 
<person id="2299" person_id="Vere, H">
Horace Vere
</person>
 in o[ne]
<newline/>
of his armes: but I hope they will both recover it quick[ly.]
<newline/>
The hinderance of that w
<super id="1393" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 was intended at Enchusen [.]
<newline/>
proceeded of the Enemy, who not fully contented w
<super id="1390" replace="ith">
t
</super>
<newline/>
persone alone of the principal party, that was contr[iver]
<newline/>
of the practise, required him to bring some other ple[edges]
<newline/>
besides, and more then could be well perfourmed, bu[t 
with
]
<newline/>
losse of longer time then could conveniently be spare[d]
<newline/>
before the siedge of Steenewicke. But the party [doth]
<newline/>
yet continue in the handes of the Enemy, and his polle[cie]
<newline/>
undiscovered. In the marchants busines, w
<super id="1406" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 her M
<super id="1403" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
<newline/>
<folioref id="1410">
fol.214r
</folioref>
 recommendeth, I have travelled as much as is possible for me:
<newline/>
and I thinke they doe rest indifferently well pleased. The
<newline/>
decision of certain points was differred by the states w
<super id="1417" replace="ith">
t
</super>
<newline/>
the companies good liking, to the end of certaine monethes,
<newline/>
w
<super id="1436" replace="hich">
ch
</super>
 when they be resumed I will helpe to end to their content.
<newline/>
<section id="1433" Section="subscription" Place="none">
And so beseeching yo
<super id="1429" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 L. to acquaint her M
<super id="1423" replace="ajestie">
tie
</super>
 w
<super id="1426" replace="ith">
t
</super>
 my dealinges,
<newline/>
I take my humble leave. Hage. June 1 1592.
</section>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
