<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="0479">
<folioref id="0002">
fol.123r
</folioref>
 
<section id="0005" Section="signmanual" Place="none">
Elizabeth R
</section>
<newline/>
<section id="0015" Section="endorsement" Place="top_right">
An Instruction to Thomas Bodleigh es
<overline id="0009" replace="quire">
q
</overline>
 our servant, sent by us to the 
<person id="0463" person_id="States General">
states generall
</person>
 of the 
<place id="0467" place_id="Low Countries">
Low Cuntries
</place>
 and the 
<person id="0471" person_id="Maurice">
Count Maurice
</person>
 for the causes followinge. given the fowrth of May 
<underline id="0012">
1594
</underline>
</section>
<newline/>
You shall use all expedition to deliver our l
<overline id="0019" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s to the generall States, or in
<newline/>
their absence to the 
<person id="0475" person_id="Council of State">
Councell of State
</person>
 whereby we have required them to give
<newline/>
you audience and to yeald to such request
<image name="es"/>
 as you shall make unto them on our
<newline/>
behalfe for the reasons followinge.
<newline/>
<newline/>
You shall declare unto them that the Spaniardes which are in 
<place id="0480" place_id="Brittany">
Bretaigne
</place>
 have of
<newline/>
late taken and fortified a speciall place in the haven of 
<place id="0483" place_id="Brest">
Brest
</place>
, whereby if they
<newline/>
shall not be speedely empeached, they shalbe commanders of that haven, being the
<newline/>
moste principall place, whereby they shall become Lordes and commanders of all the
<newline/>
trade by sea westward, ether towardes 
<place id="0486" place_id="Bordeaux">
Bourdeaux
</place>
, 
<place id="0489" place_id="La Rochelle">
Rochell
</place>
, 
<place id="0492" place_id="Spain">
Spaine
</place>
, or other places
<newline/>
westard whatsoever, and thereby shall also empeach and interupt all manner of
<newline/>
marchant
<image name="es"/>
 passing from the east toward the west, as all men of knowledge and
<newline/>
understandinge of the situation of that haven being one of the best havens in Europe
<newline/>
and so neare to the streight betwixt 
<place id="0496" place_id="England">
England
</place>
 and 
<place id="0499" place_id="France">
Fraunce
</place>
, may very well consider
<newline/>
and fynde most necessary to be in the beginning with speed withstood. For which
<newline/>
cause you shall lette them knowe that we have caused the sayd fortification so begunne
<newline/>
by the Spaniardes to be be viewed, and the meanes also discouvered howe with con-
<newline/>
venient force by sea, and with men to enter uppon the lande, the same enterprise of
<newline/>
the Spaniard may be (if it be taken in hande speedely) ether defeated or made frustrate
<newline/>
For which purpose we are determined to send certain shipping thither with a
<newline/>
number of men to attempt this service, and for the more expedition besides some
<newline/>
good numbers otherwise levyed and provided within o
<super id="0044" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 realme, we require the
<newline/>
States to yeald some succor also by shipping on their part to accompanie ours accor-
<newline/>
ding as is by speciall contract covenanted on their part. because the Spaniardes
<newline/>
have already armed certain shippes and doe use them betwixt our Coast
<image name="es"/>
 of Eng-
<newline/>
land and the partes of Fraunce toward the landes end of England where they
<newline/>
have already taken some of our subject
<image name="es"/>
 shippes, And beside that we understand
<newline/>
by report that the Spaniardes doe mean to bring into that haven some new forces
<newline/>
of shipping which they are preparing newely in Spayne wholy to possesse
<newline/>
the sayd Harboroughe, being able to harborrugh and hold above a thowsand shipes
<newline/>
of the greatest burden. And the greater number of shipping that they will
<newline/>
yeald unto us they shall not onely therein greately content us but further that
<newline/>
which shalbe proffitable for them and their generall state, which cannot be but
<newline/>
damnefied and endaungered, considering the maintenance of the State of those
<newline/>
Cuntries consisteth uppon the free trade of Navigation unto the west partes
<newline/>
thorough our narrowe seas. And this ayd of theirs we require to be
<newline/>
<catchword id="0063">
speedely
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0067">
fol.123v
</folioref>
 speedely given, and to be sent towardes 
<place id="0502" place_id="Plymouth">
Portesmowth
</place>
 or 
<place id="0505" place_id="Plymouth">
Plimmo
<missing id="0070" type="fire">
uth
</missing>
</place>
<newline/>
westerly portes of our realme where they shall have knowledge
<newline/>
with our Navye which we have ordered speedely to repaire towa
<missing id="0075" type="fire">
[rdes]
</missing>
<newline/>
of Brest.
<newline/>
<newline/>
Secondely you shall lett them knowe that we require to have suche 
<missing id="0081" type="fire">
[sub]
</missing>
<newline/>
ject
<image name="es"/>
 as be there in our pay to be speedely brought from thence to the 
<missing id="0098" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
shipped there and brought to joyne with other our forces levyed and 
<missing id="0101" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
to goe by sea toward the sayd porte of Brest; for conduction of wh
<missing id="0104" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
<person id="0508" person_id="Baskerville, T">
S
<super id="0089" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Thomas Baskerville
</person>
 knight to take the generall charge of the 
<missing id="0107" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
to bring them from thence by Sea, to whom we require the States 
<missing id="0110" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
nable Commission for the saffe passage of him and the sayd compani
<missing id="0113" type="fire">
[e]
</missing>
<newline/>
where he shall fynde them unto the Sea side, And that he may h
<missing id="0116" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
to take up and give sufficient shipping in Zealand for the transp
<missing id="0119" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
sayd numbers uppon reasonable hyre of the same.
<newline/>
<newline/>
And though we did readely yeald of late at the request of the St
<missing id="0154" type="fire">
<missing id="0122" type="fire">
ates
</missing>
</missing>
<newline/>
cause to be Levyed one thowsand five hundred soldiors within our re
<missing id="0157" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
sent over thither by 
<person id="0511" person_id="Vere, F">
S
<super id="0127" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Frauncis Veer
</person>
, and did also direct to be sen
<missing id="0160" type="fire">
[t]
</missing>
<newline/>
under the 
<person id="0514" person_id="Maurice">
Count Maurice
</person>
 other numbers which before had served 
<missing id="0163" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
some also out of 
<place id="0517" place_id="Flushing">
Vlissing
</place>
 and 
<place id="0542" place_id="Brill">
Brile
</place>
 &amp; other places: Yet we did
<newline/>
yeald these succors to them uppon condition (and not otherwise) that
<newline/>
that we should have cause given us by anie accident following 
<missing id="0166" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
service of these our people, they should uppon our request returne 
<missing id="0169" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
service in anie place that we should command them. And th
<missing id="0172" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
we doe imagine they will be loath to forbeare the service of these 
<missing id="0175" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
because of their purpose by the defence of 
<place id="0520" place_id="Coevorden">
Covarden
</place>
 to recouver the 
<missing id="0178" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
ghen, a matter we cannot denye but may be beneficiall unto the
<missing id="0181" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
comparable in common benefitte to the defeating of this purpose 
<missing id="0184" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
for the possessing of Brest. And the matter touching us so neare 
<missing id="0187" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
cannot forbeare to seake to have the ayd of o
<super id="0523" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 owne people being a 
<missing id="0190" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
bound to serve us before anie others. Whereuppon you shall earn
<missing id="0193" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
them that they will give order to all such that be our naturall 
<missing id="0196" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
there serving in bandes may be licenced to return under the charge 
<missing id="0199" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
S
<super id="0146" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Thomas Baskervyle. And if they shall object that the 
<missing id="0202" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
newley Levyed by S
<super id="0150" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Frauncis Veer are in their pay and have be 
<missing id="0205" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
their charges. Yet you shall say that we thinke considering the 
<missing id="0208" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0212">
fol.124r
</folioref>
 doe owe us, and that they never did yeald us anie benefitte in money or other-
<newline/>
wise towardes the recompense of our excessive charges these manie yeares; they
<newline/>
may forbeare that charge. And if otherwise they will not freely yeald it unto
<newline/>
us as some token of their good will, we shall be content that such sommes of
<newline/>
money as have been defrayed by them for their levye, and their wages there,
<newline/>
may be accompted as a portion of the debte which they owe us, whereof we
<newline/>
shall acquitte them. And because we thinke they will hardely be induced here
<newline/>
unto: we are contented that uppon the peremptory refusall hereof for the
<newline/>
yealding to us of the service of these xv
<super id="0292" replace="">
C
</super>
 so newely levyed: You shall pre-
<newline/>
cisely require them that the rest of o
<super id="0227" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 Companies being footemen that went
<newline/>
from 
<place id="0526" place_id="Ostend">
Ostend
</place>
 and other places towardes their service being in o
<super id="0231" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 pay may be
<newline/>
returned. Adding that you will advertise us of such reasons as they shall
<newline/>
alleage for the stay of the others, giving them some hope that if they will give
<newline/>
some ayd of shippinge according to the contract, and give expedition for the
<newline/>
returninge of our sayd numbers being now in their service and in our pay
<newline/>
We may be the better contented with their manner of aunsweares. But
<newline/>
in no wise you shall accept of them anie argument
<image name="es"/>
 or aunsweares for the
<newline/>
delay of the sending away of these our men that are in o
<super id="0242" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 pay wherein we
<newline/>
doe not meane to have anie of our horsemen to be revoked. And if
<newline/>
it shall so happen that they will (as here tofore they have), stand in termes.
<newline/>
not to commande the comming away of our people by their Commission, but
<newline/>
shall yeald to suffer them: Then you shall give S
<super id="0250" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Frauncis Veer knowledge
<newline/>
of our pleasure for the reduction of them from thence as you shall prescribe
<newline/>
unto him for which purpose you shall have our l
<overline id="0255" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s to him to followe
<newline/>
yo
<super id="0259" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 direction.
<newline/>
<newline/>
Item. because we take it that these our people are at this present in the
<newline/>
field towardes 
<place id="0529" place_id="Friesland">
Friseland
</place>
 under the commandement of Count 
<highlight id="0269" Type="italic">
Maurice
</highlight>
 as
<newline/>
Generall of the armie of the States: you shall have our l
<overline id="0266" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s also of
<newline/>
Credette to him, to whom you shall ether by yo
<super id="0276" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 l
<overline id="0273" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s, or by yo
<super id="0279" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 selfe if
<newline/>
conveniently you may repayre to the Campes imparte these former
<newline/>
reasons herebefore expressed to be shewed to the States for the having of o
<super id="0284" replace="ur">
r
</super>
<newline/>
people from thence to this service above expressed. And if you shall
<newline/>
fynde it difficulte to have the service of the xv
<super id="0289" replace="">
C
</super>
 newely levyed under th 
<catchword id="0295">
charge
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0301">
fol.124v
</folioref>
 charge of S
<super id="0545" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Frauncis Veer: Then you shall lette the sayd S
<super id="0310" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 F
<missing id="0316" type="fire">
raunci
</missing>
s understand
<newline/>
that we are contented that he shall continew there with them, and 
<missing id="0313" type="fire">
[he]
</missing>
 shall use
<newline/>
all the expedition he can to return from thence under the charge of 
<missing id="0327" type="fire">
S
<super id="0319" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Tho
</missing>
mas Basker
<newline/>
vyle all the rest of the Companies that are in o
<super id="0307" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 pay. And for 
<missing id="0330" type="fire">
[the ch]
</missing>
arges of
<newline/>
their reduction from thence and their embarking: we have given o
<missing id="0336" type="fire">
[rder to]
</missing>
 S
<super id="0333" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Thomas
<newline/>
Baskervyle shalbe furnished with money for the same purpose. 
<missing id="0339" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 as soone
<newline/>
as you have obtained this our request, considering we understa
<missing id="0347" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 you have
<newline/>
cause for yo
<super id="0344" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 own private busines to returne hither, we are con
<missing id="0354" type="fire">
[tent you]
</missing>
 shall so doe
<newline/>
not doubting but you will employ yo
<super id="0351" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 selfe to the uttermoste 
<missing id="0360" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 as much
<newline/>
of these our request
<image name="es"/>
 as possibly you may.
<newline/>
<newline/>
If o
<super id="0365" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 forces which we require to be returned are so farre pas
<missing id="0373" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 Frizeland
<newline/>
as a long tyme shalbe passed before they can be returned a
<missing id="0376" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
ht to
<newline/>
Flushing to be there embarked. Then we have determined 
<missing id="0379" type="fire">
[S
<super id="0370" replace="ir">
r
</super>
]
</missing>
 Thomas
<newline/>
Baskervyle fynding the same to require longer tyme to be 
<missing id="0391" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 from
<newline/>
Frizeland, then one service shall require, shall by vertue 
<missing id="0394" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 to the
<newline/>
<person id="0533" person_id="Sidney, R">
Gouvernors of Flushing
</person>
, 
<person id="0539" person_id="Burgh, T">
the Brile
</person>
, and 
<person id="0536" person_id="Norris, E">
Ostend
</person>
 receav
<missing id="0397" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 companie
<newline/>
as shall make one thowsand &amp; one hundred men which he 
<missing id="0400" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 all speed
<newline/>
that he may cause to be shipped at Flushing and Ostend, 
<missing id="0403" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 them to
<newline/>
<place id="0548" place_id="Portsmouth">
Portesmowth
</place>
 For supply whereof we will that S
<super id="0388" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Fraun
<missing id="0406" type="fire">
[cis Veer]
</missing>
 shall send
<newline/>
from Frizeland or the Camp so manie of o
<super id="0410" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 forces as are 
<missing id="0413" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 under him
<newline/>
to the sayd number of one thowsand one hundred to serv
<missing id="0421" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 sayde
<newline/>
Townes of Flushing, Brile and Ostend. And this o
<super id="0418" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 
<missing id="0424" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
tion you
<newline/>
shall impart to the States if you fynde likelihood that th
<missing id="0433" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 cannot
<newline/>
be brought with such speed as the service requireth and p
<missing id="0436" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 same to
<newline/>
be executed, of which o
<super id="0430" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 purpose we have by o
<super id="0442" replace="ur">
r
</super>
 l
<overline id="0445" replace="ettre">
re
</overline>
s cert
<missing id="0439" type="fire">
[ified to]
</missing>
 Frauncis
<newline/>
Veer to whom you shall send the same.
<newline/>
For a further reason to induce the States to yeald to the send
<missing id="0456" type="fire">
[ing .]
</missing>
 of these
<newline/>
companies demaunded you may lett them knowe that 
<missing id="0459" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 shall
<newline/>
see that such men as we spare for their service cannot be 
<missing id="0462" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 our owne
<newline/>
Coast
<image name="es"/>
 are in daunger, they wilbe sory to be at charge of 
<missing id="0476" type="fire">
[.]
</missing>
 sending
<newline/>
forth 
<insertion id="0466">
to
</insertion>
 their continewall consumption.
<newline/>
<section id="0470" Section="subscription" Place="base_right">
<person id="0552" person_id="Burghley">
William Burghley
</person>
</section>
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
