<transcript>
<page num="1">
<lettertext id="0117">
<folioref id="0002">
fol.122r
</folioref>
 3 May 1594. Instructions given to M
<super id="0007" replace="aster">
r
</super>
 Thomas Bode-
<newline/>
leigh, being sent to the 
<person id="0119" person_id="States General">
States Generall
</person>
 and 
<person id="0122" person_id="Council of State">
Counsell of Estate
</person>
,
<newline/>
and the 
<person id="0125" person_id="Maurice">
Counte Maurice
</person>
 for these hereafter following.
<newline/>
<newline/>
To deliver the letters with all expedition, and to desire audience.
<newline/>
<newline/>
To declare unto them that the Spaniards, which are in 
<place id="0128" place_id="Brittany">
Brittagnie
</place>
 have
<newline/>
taken and fortified an especiall 
<insertion id="0015">
place
</insertion>
 in the Haven of 
<place id="0131" place_id="Brest">
Brest
</place>
; if they be not em-
<newline/>
peached, they will be commanders of it, whereby they shall become Lords
<newline/>
of all the trade westward, either towards 
<place id="0137" place_id="Bordeaux">
Bourdeaux
</place>
, 
<place id="0140" place_id="La Rochelle">
Rochell
</place>
, 
<place id="0143" place_id="Spain">
Spayne
</place>
,
<newline/>
or other places westward whatsoever. They shall also empeach the
<newline/>
trade from the East towards the West. Which in the beginning 
<deletion id="0022">
we
</deletion>
 must
<newline/>
with speed withstood. For that cause you shall lett them
<newline/>
knowe that wee caused the fortification to be viewed, and discovered,
<newline/>
by which meanes this entreprise of the Spaniards might either be
<newline/>
defeated, or made frustrate. That wee determined to send some shipps
<newline/>
with a nomber of men to attempt this service, wee require the States
<newline/>
to yeeld some succor, according as by especiall contract is covenanted.
<newline/>
That they Spaniards have taken alreadie some of our shipps, and
<newline/>
are preparing in Spaine new forces of shipping to place in the
<newline/>
same haven, which is able to hold 1000 shipps of the greater
<newline/>
burden. That the more shipps will send us, the grealier they
<newline/>
will content us, and their Generall State can not be damnified
<newline/>
by it, considering the maintenance of the State of those Countries
<newline/>
consisteth uppon the trade of navegation into the west partes
<newline/>
thorough our Narrow Seas, and this aide of theirs to be speedilie
<newline/>
given, and to be sent towards 
<place id="0146" place_id="Plymouth">
Plimmouth
</place>
, 
<place id="0149" place_id="Portsmouth">
Portsmouth
</place>
, or other
<newline/>
westerlie ports of our Realme, where they shall have know-
<newline/>
ledge how to meete with our Navie, which wee have ordered
<newline/>
speedilie to repaire towards the said Haven of Brest. Secondlie
<newline/>
that such soldiors and forces of our Subjects, as be there in our
<newline/>
paie maie be shipped over, and putt in order to goe by Sea to-
<newline/>
wards the Port of Brest, under the conduct of 
<person id="0152" person_id="Baskerville, T">
S
<super id="0046" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Thomas
<newline/>
Baskerville
</person>
 Knight, whom wee have sent to take the generall
<newline/>
charge of the said nombers. And although wee did levie uppon
<newline/>
the request of the States 1500 souldiors, yet wer it done upon such
<newline/>
condition, that if wee should have cause given us by anie accident
<newline/>
following to have the service of these our People they should
<newline/>
returne uppon our request retourne from thence to our service
<newline/>
in anie place wee should command them. And albeit wee doe imagine
<newline/>
they will be loath to forbeare their service, because of their purpose
<newline/>
by the defence of 
<place id="0155" place_id="Coevorden">
Covarden
</place>
 to recover the towne of 
<place id="0158" place_id="Groningen">
Groninghen
</place>
, a matter
<newline/>
wee can not denie, it maie be beneficiall unto them yet nothing com-
<newline/>
parable in common benefitt to defeating of his purpose of the
<newline/>
Spaniard for the possessing of Brest, whereuppon you shall earnestlie
<newline/>
require that they maie be licenced to returne under the charge of
<newline/>
<catchword id="0063">
the
</catchword>
<newline/>
<folioref id="0067">
fol.122v
</folioref>
 the aforesaid knight. If they alleadge, that the 1500 which were
<newline/>
newlie levied by 
<person id="0162" person_id="Vere, F">
S
<super id="0071" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Francis Veer
</person>
, are now in their paie, and have
<newline/>
bene levied at their charges, you maie replie that wee considering
<newline/>
the great debtes they doe us and that they never did yeelde us anie
<newline/>
benefitt in monie, or otherwise, they maie forbeare that charge, if
<newline/>
they will not, that wee will be content, that such s
<overline id="0078" replace="um">
u
</overline>
mes of monie as
<newline/>
have bene defraied by them of their levie, and their wages, 
<deletion id="0082">
w
</deletion>
 maie
<newline/>
be accompted as a 
<insertion id="0165">
portion of a
</insertion>
 debt which they owe us, whereof wee shall
<newline/>
acquite them. which if they denie you shall preciselie require that
<newline/>
those companies which being in our paie, were taken out of 
<place id="0168" place_id="Ostend">
Ostende
</place>
,
<newline/>
and other places shall be returned, and you shall take no answers for
<newline/>
the delaying of those men, that be in our paie. And if they will not
<newline/>
yeeld no waies to our request, you shall 
<deletion id="0171">
[.]
</deletion>
 give Francis Veer
<newline/>
to understand our pleasure of the reduction of them from
<newline/>
thence. An because wee thinke that 
<deletion id="0096">
wee think
</deletion>
 our is in 
<place id="0174" place_id="Friesland">
Frieze
<newline/>
land
</place>
 with Counte Maurice in his campe, wee will you that you
<newline/>
shewe letters of creditt unto him. And if you find it difficult
<newline/>
to have the service of the 1500 newelie levied, then tell S
<super id="0102" replace="ir">
r
</super>
<newline/>
Francis Veer, that wee be content that should tarie there,
<newline/>
but give good order, to send over those which are in our paie.
<newline/>
<newline/>
And if they be so farr gone into Friezland with Counte
<newline/>
Maurice, that it will be long ere they can be embarqued
<newline/>
and doe us service, you shall have our letters of creditt to the
<newline/>
<person id="0177" person_id="Sidney, R">
Gouvernors of Flushing
</person>
, 
<person id="0180" person_id="Norris, E">
Ostende
</person>
 &amp;c. to levie 1000 men there
<newline/>
to be brought over, which ought to be supplied again
 
out of
<newline/>
the campe by direction of S
<super id="0114" replace="ir">
r
</super>
 Francis Veer.
</lettertext>
</page>
</transcript>
